Welcome to this new section, and in this
section you're going to learn how to
build a real world program that allows the
user to store information about books, so
I have already builded a program and I'll
show you step by step how you can do the
same. I have the program here and it's an
executable file.
So apart from learning how to build the
a dot py program ,you'll also to learn how
to build executable files and that run on
windows and dot app files that run on Mac.
So you can basically, you give your
program to anyone and they don't need to
have Python installed in their computer.
So I called the program Bookstore, and this
was built mainly with tkinter which is a
graphical user interface library and the
SQLite3 library which is a library
to interact with SQLite database. So what
we got here are four entries where you
can enter a new book record, so let's say
you've got a new book in your store and
you want to add it in your database.
And here you can see all the books that have
been added to the program. You can add a
new book, let's say pythons for title.
Ardit, quickly and 1918. You have the ISBN
number which is a unique identification
number for books. It's quite long.
Let's say like that, and you add entry and
then you view all again. And you'll see
that the new entry was added to the
database, so every record that you see
here is actually stored in a table inside
this itel1 database. Let me add some
other buttons here. So if you want you
can actually search for entry, for record.
Search entry and then it will
display the entry that you searched.
When you click on the entry you get all the
fields displayed in each of the text box here.
So, view all again and you can also
update and delete the records.
And finally you can close the window.
So it's not a great user interface.
I'm not a great user interface designer,
but you will learn a lot by
building this program, so it's quite a
long one but it will pay off.
So let's kick it off.