Hi there, and in this lecture what you're
going to do is start to build our
Bookstore program, and specifically we're
going to work on the graphical user
interface because you know this program
has two parts so to say. So it has a
backend and it has frontend.
The backend is the sqlite3
database code, so the code that interacts
with the database and the frontend is a code
of the Tkinter library, so the code that
builds up all these buttons, these
entries, this text, this list box, and
this scroll bar. So normally you'd have
to choose whether you want to work on
the backend code first or you want to
start building the frontend code but
first of all though the very first thing
you want to do is actually to start
defining some requirements. So you want
to see what your program will do.
So let's say you want your program to show
a list of the current records, so when
you press view all, you see the list of
records here, and then you want your
program to search a current entry, and
then you want to add entry and update
and select data, and then you want your
program to close the window. So basically
these are our requirements and now you
can choose to start writing the backend
so you could write a function that
selects all the data from the database
and then you could return those data as text.
So you can just print them out just for
now if you want to write the backend
first because you don't have the frontend.
You don't have a graphical
user interface built yet, so you can just
write the functions of the backend and then
print out the output, or you can start
writing the front end first, so you build
this graphical user interface, but when
you click those buttons nothing happens.
So basically you just draw this thing
with Python, and then once you have done
that, you start building the backend and
then you connect all these widgets,
all the commands of these buttons,
with your back-end functions.
So it's a matter of preference whether you
choose to work with the back end or the
front end first. In this course, in this
section we're going to build the front
end first, so we're going to build
a graphical user interface that will do
nothing for a while until we connect it
to the backend. All right then, I would
like to first remove this vertical bar
here because I'm going to draw the
graphical user interface here, so I'll go,
I'm going to make a sketch for you to see
and to have a sketch in here all the time.
So to remove this bar if
you're curious you can just go to
settings, then there is a package that
actually shows that bar that's called
Wrap guide and you want to display,
so this displays the line at the eightieth
character in the editor, and that may
help you if you want, it may help you to
keep a particular pattern, so you don't
want to have more than 80 characters in
your code. So that bar helps you keep that row.
Anyway we don't want that
so I just removed it, and I'm just going
to write a few notes inside the doc string.
So you know that the doc string
is like a comment line, so if you put
any anything inside these triple quotes
this is not read as code by Python, but
it's just like a documentation string,
so just for humans to read. So let's say
I want a program that stores this book
information, so Title and Author. Year, and
ISBN, so the identification number for
books, and the user can view all records.
They can search an entry
and add an entry, update an entry.
Delete and they can close the program
if they want. Close. Great so if you start
thinking about that and now you'd want
to have a graphical user interface that
has all these buttons, so that the user
can do these actions through some
buttons, and then you think about how
they can view records and you know that
Tkinter has the Listbox widget that
allows you to display text as a list, so
line by line, and then you want the user
to search an entry, add an entry, update
entry, so you need some entry widgets.
And then of course you'd want some labels
that can tell what each entry is about,
so that would be a label widget.
And you may also want a scrollbar,
so that your list is scrollable, so if
there are many records the user can
scroll through them and they can see
the records under the list, and so
we've got a sketch. This of course
requires some fantasy and maybe some
experience with user interface design,
but it's very important that you
have a sketch, so I'm going to keep this
sketch on the screen while I code the program.
Normally in real life you'd want to have
a drawing maybe on real paper,
or just on a digital screen, but it's
important to have it, and now that we
have it let's start building it
in the next lecture.