Great, so now we have a sketch of our
graphical user interface and that should
make things easier, so now you can just
go ahead and code your graphical user
interface in Python using the Tkinter
features, so Tkinter is a library that
we'll be using to make this interface.
And I suppose you already know Tkinter
because I explained that in one of the
previous sections, so if you don't know
Tkinter, please go back two sections
before this, and then you'll be able to
understand what I am talking about here.
So I'll keep the sketch on the right and
now you know that to make a graphical
user interface with Tkinter, you can
either use the pack method to pack your
widgets, or the grid method. We'll be using
the grid method, so it could be a good
idea to actually make a grid on your
sketch, so that when you create your
widgets, let's say you create a button,
you'd want to pass the number of the row and
the number of the column, so having a grid
like this will make things easier.
Alright, and I just like to delete this
doc string. We don't need it and it saves
me space so that you can see
a cleaner workspace here. Alright, from
Tkinter import everything, so I'm not
explaining the code now because you
already know these things. If there is
something new, I'll go through it.
Window equals to Tk, so the Tk method that
creates a window object, and then you
want to apply the main loop method which
is basically a way to wrap up all the
widgets that you will enter in this
space now. Alright, so we have four
labels here so we have a label title, and
author, year, and ISBN, so I'm just going
to create four labels or four label
objects. So I'll name my objects,
my variables from l1 to l4.
And we use the label object, label method
for that. Window is the parent window and
text would be title. So control enter you
can go to the next line no matter where
you are in the previous line, so you
don't have to just switch go to here and
then press enter. You just you just press
control enter and you go to the next line.
And then you apply the grid method,
so the first label is on row 0, column 0 as well.
Then you can just copy this and paste
it three more times. So that would be l2,
l3, and l4, and you'd also want to change
the text of your label here, and ISBN.
Author would be column 2 as you see from
the sketch, so 0 2. Then we have the year.
0, 1 and then 1, 2 for the last label. So let's
see what we have. I'd just like to call my script.
Alright, looks promising.
Now let's add the entries, so these were
static widgets. Now we need to add some
entries, so e1 would be entry and the
entry gets the window as the first
parameter just like any other widget does.
And also a text variable parameter,
and this text variable parameter, this
expects as an argument the value that
the user will enter in the entry widget.
And that is a spatial data type.
So you first need to actually create
a data type here, an object with all that
data type, so let's call it. We are
creating an entry for the title.
Say title text equal to StringVar, so this
is the function that creates this
spatial object, and that would be equal
to the title text, so that's it. And you
also need to grid this entry widget.
So grid and the first widgets of the title
widgets corresponds with row 0 and column 1.
So that's it. I can quickly multiply
this here. Author, text. Year, text.
And ISBN text. You also need to change the
numbers of the variables. Just like that.
And of course you need to pass that.
This user entries in here. So it should
be n, and this too. Alright and lastly you
want to specify the rows and columns for
these entries too, so it should be 0, 3
and then we have the year text widget 1,
1, alright, and the last entry 1, 3.
Alright, let's check it out.
Yep, looks good.
Great, and now it's the turn of the Listbox.
So let's call it list1. Why not?
And that would be equal to List box window.
And then you would want to specify
the height of your Listbox and width
as well, so I thought about putting 6 and 35.
It would be good height and width.
You can you can test different
heights and widths and see what comes
better, and then I would like to grid this.
So grid. And so this would start at row
number two and column zero, however if we
leave it like this
things will not go as we expect actually.
We can try this, and as you can see the
list box occupied over only the
first cell, so the first cell of the
first column on row zero, one, two, so row 2,
column zero. What we want instead
is to span this listbox
on the other columns as well, and on the
other rows because we will have
buttons here later, so we want to span that.
And you can see the sketch here, so we
can add rowspan parameter, and that
would be equal to six and column span
as well, so that would be two, alright.
So that would be a list box, however we also
need to actually add a scrollbar there,
so that the list can be scrolled
when there are lots of data in list, lots
of records. To attach a scrollbar to the
list, the logic here works like this.
You create your scrollbar and then you tell
your scrollbar about the list that the
scrollbar has to scroll, and then you
tell your list as well who it's
scrollbar is, so let's first create
the scroll bar, an independent scroll bar.
So let's say sb1 Scrollbar method, and that
is attached to the window, and then you
apply the grid method, so the scroll bar
would be our row 1, column 3. And once you
created these two objects you want to
apply a configure method to the list box,
and a configure method to the scroll bar
object, and these configure methods
get arguments, so this would be
scrollcommand equals sb1.set.
That's it.
So meaning that the vertical scroll bar
along the y-axis will be set to this
scroll bar and then you go to the scroll
bar method. Sorry this has to be
configure, then you pass command equals
to list1.yview, so that should work.
You are passing a command
parameter here, so meaning that when you
scroll the bar, the view, the vertical
view of the list will change, so let's
see how this goes. And seems like
I've messed up something here, I have
put the position of the scroll bar on
row one I guess and column three, yeah.
So the scroll bar should be actually row two,
column two, let's check that again.
Yeah, seems to be working, though it doesn't
look very centered because we need to
span it through the same rows as we
have spanned the listbox here, so we
need to add here rowspan parameter, set
it to 6 and now the scroll bar
looks centered.
All right so now what we have left is to
add these button widgets just here, great.
So we have six buttons, let's start with
the first one, we have the button method.
Window and texts. Our buttons have text.
View all is the first one, and then I
thought of putting a width of 12, so b1
grid, that would be row 2, column three.
And have five more buttons, so I'll paste this.
Six I think, so b2, b3, 4 and 6.
Of course these buttons don't have
a command parameter now because later we
will add here a command parameter and that
will decide what the buttons will do, but
for now that is just fine, so these
buttons will be aligned in column three
all of them, and everyone has a different
row value. And six. Great, so let's see
what we got, and boom! I forgot to put
a row number for the close button. Seven.
And how it looks better. So this was how
to build a graphical user interface.
Of course these buttons don't do anything
for now, so in the next lecture I'll show
you how to attach actions to this
graphical user interface, so we will work
on the backend and we'll be using
SQLite 3 for interacting with the
database and fetching those data in
this graphical user interface, so I hope
my routines and my practices will help
you to build the graphical user interfaces
with ease, and I'll see you in
the next lecture.