Hey welcome to this new lecture and here
we are continuing to build our bookstore
program that stores and retrieves book
records from a database. So far as you
know we have been the graphical user
interface with tkinter, so this is our
script. So basically we have the front
end of our program, and now so this is
our graphical user interface and
basically what we need to do now is
to attach some functions to all these
buttons, so let's say for example when we
press the view all button a function
will be trigger that selects data from
the SQLite database, and then gets those data
and put them all these listbox here, so
that means we need to create a database
an SQLite database with SQLite3 and we
also need to create a table first, so we
could do this in the script, but I prefer
to actually create another script and
then import that script in here.
So, import, let's call the new script
backend, so we need to create the backend
dot py script all right and I also want
to change the name of this,
of my frontend scripts, so that we keep
the same pattern, so let's say frontend.
Alright, so we are in frontend script now
and here we are in the backend script so
what that means is let's say you create
a view function, so that selects data
from the database and you create that
function here, and then you go to the
view all button and then you'd add
a command parameter here, and that would be
equal to let's say command just to give
you an idea. Command equals to backend
and the name of the function.
So something like that.
Alright, hope this makes sense.
However for now it would be great if we
forget about this script, so we need to
keep in mind the graphical user
interface but it's good not to interact
with these widgets for now, so what we do
instead is print out the output
of the functions, the function that
we built as strings in the command
line here. So will not throw those data
in the list box, but in the terminal here.
Alright, let's start coding, import
sqlite3. That is the first thing you want
to do, and I'll keep an image of the
graphical user interface here so that he
it's easy for you to refer to it.
So we need to create a view function, but
before that I would like to create a
database, so a connection to the database.
And I would like to put that inside
a function, so let's say function connect.
And we have a connection object, so that
would be sqlite3.connect, and let's
call what database books.db.
Alright, so we establish a connection to
the database, then we define a cursor
object like that and next we need to
execute an SQL statement, so cursor
object execute and inside double quotes
we input the SQL statement. So we have a
database and we also need a table in the
database where to store or book information.
Now think about that. When the user,
when you give this program to the
user they will execute the program and
every time they execute the program your
script has to check if there is an
existing table in a books database, so if
there is a table you'd say don't create
the table. If there is not a table,
you'd want to create the table, so create
table if not exists, and let's call table
book just to differentiate it from the
database name, and then you'd want to
pass some parameters. The first parameter
I would like to pass is the ID.
Don't confuse is with the ISBN number,
the book identification. This is just a
number that will start from zero and it
will auto increment by one so that we
have control of how many records we have
in the database, so it's a good idea to
have this ID here and that would be an
integer and you need to set it to
primary key, so that's mandatory column
in your table and you have title as text.
Author as text, year as integer, and ISBN.
That's an integer as well. Aright, that's it.
You want to commit your changes
and then close the connection. Alright, so we
created a connect function. Later when we
will run this script, so the frontend
script and then you import backend,
this script, the script on the backend,
so the code of the backend
will be read by Python, but if you
haven't called this function, this code
will not be executed. So what you want to
do instead is to have this function
executed any time you'd execute this
function, so you execute the frontend
and this imports backend, so it executes
all the code and this line here is
executed, so a function will run
any time you run the frontend. Alright.
I hope that makes sense or let me
quickly explain that better. So we have
an A dot py script, and we have
a B dot py script, and in the A dot py script
we import the B script and what
we have in the B script is a function
through that prints out something on the
screen, 'Hey', and save this and save this
as well, so when you execute a dot py
nothing happens for now because you have
just defined your script, but if you call
the script here, alright, save and
execute A again. This time you'll get the
the output of the function.
So that's the idea. Thanks.
And back to our real world script.
Alright, now we have the connect function.
Let's start by creating an insert
function, so a function that
will insert some data in the database.
So I'm starting with the insert function
because that's, because that's an easier
function than the other one, so I'd like
to start from the easy things first.
Def insert, so that's how I call my function,
and think about that. You have four
entries there so you expect from the
user to enter a title, author, and a year,
and an ISBN number. So you want to pass
four parameters here, and ISBN. Alright.
And then of course you need to
connect to the database because this
function here it will just connect to
the database temporarily and it will
check if there is a table and it will
close the connection, so you have a closed
connection here. When you when you press
the insert button, well when you press
the add entry button you need to create
a new connection to the database.
And let me go ahead and get these two
lines as well because we need them too.
Alright, and here is where
where we execute our specific SQL
statement inside quotes. So what the add
entry button will do is conserved into
book so the table book values, and here
is a trick now. We have an id here,
so this is an auto increment value, so we
don't have to pass that manually and what
we can do instead is pass a null value
here and Python understand that and it
will create the id automatically, and then
we have for question marks. One for each
of our values, and then you need to pass your
parameters as a second parameter over
the execute function so as a tuple here.
Title, author, year, and ISBN, all right.
Let me write another function, and then we
execute the script to try it and see how
it is going, so def let's save the
view function, so this will fetch
all the rows of the table,
so we copy this and put them here, so we
connect to the database, create a cursor
object, and then we execute an SQL
statement, and then because this this
would be a select statement so will not
perform any changes to the database
we don't need a commit method here. And this
is actually quite simple. Select all from
book, so you actually need to return your
selection as a tuple, and then you grab
that selection and you put that in the
list box, so you want the view function
to return a tuple, so let's say
rows equals to cur.fetchall.
And then you can close the connection,
but your data will be stored will
remain stored in the rows variable, so
you can just return rows here, alright.
So let's try out the script now, and the
way to try it out would be to use a
print statement, so we'd want to call
insert and then we would enter some data
manually, so in the real program this
insert function will be executed
somewhere in the add entry button,
but for now we need to keep things simple
and reach our objective step-by-step so
insert let's pass some values here, title.
Let's say "The sea" and then author John Tablet.
Alright and year is an integer,
so you just need to pass a number and ISBN
also is an integer so no need to
put them inside quotes, and then you
would also want to print out the output
of the view function. Great, so let's
see how this goes.
That'll be the backend script.
Great, so the record was
inserted into the database and it was
printed out from the view function.
If you execute the script again, you'll get
two records because the insert function was
executed two times. Alright, seems to be
going well, so what else do we have?
We have a search function and we would
implement an or search, so what that
means is that the user will enter a title,
or an author name, or the year,
or the ISBN number, or he may choose to
enter all of them at the same time,
but if let's say he enters the year only
he'll get all the rows corresponding to that year.
So here we need to pass four parameters
as well, ISBN, alright. And then we need
these lines of code, so connects to the
database, cursor objects, and then
execute, so let's stay here for a while.
We want to select all from book where
title is equal to something or author
is equal to something, or year equals to
something, or ISBN, and then the second
parameter would be the tuple of the
arguments, title, author, year, ISBN, and then
we need to fetch all the rows that will be
returned from this query, and store them
in these rows variable, close the
connection, and again return rows.
Alright, one problem here though that we
may encounter is that the user may want
to pass let's say the author name only
to the entries, so this function will get
only the arguments for the author
parameter and these other parameters
will remain without a value, and then
you'll get an error because your
function is designed to have four
parameters. In that case you'd want to
pass some empty strings as default values.
Alright, this too. So now if the
user passes an author name, let's say
John Smith this SQL statement will search
for an empty title, or for the author name
John Smith, or for an empty year, or ISBN
and so on, and it will return all the rows
with John Smith as author name.
Alright, so let's save this and try it out.
So we have connect, insert, connect,
print view. Let's say "The earth". I'm
inserting another record here. John Smith.
Alright, and then let's say print search and
you want to pass some arguments.
For example author equals to John Smith, alright.
Without a quote here and let's see
how this goes.
So we got here this list of rows from
the view function because we also have
a view function here and then the search
function returned this row for us.
So the row with ID 3 and with John Smith
as author, so that is working well.
Let's go ahead and build a delete function now.
So think about how the users want to
delete a record? So most probably they'd
want you to see or some records in
the list box, and that they would want to
select one of the records, let's say the
record for ID 3, "The earth", John Smith etc.
So they would select that and then would press
the delete button. So that means we want
to first grab the list selection, so the
selection from the list box. We would grab
that as a tuple, but we'll think about
that later, so we'll grab that as a tuple
and then that tuple has a unique identification
number, so the ID, so we would want to
refer to that ID and then go to our database
table and delete the row with that ID.
So hope that is not very confusing and in the
delete function so we would expect
the ID of the tuple
that the user will select.
And then we would want to have this code
and start from there, so connect to the
database cursor object execute a statement.
Alright, let's see how
this goes.
So we want to delete from book where ID
is equal to something, great and then
that's something is the ID parameter,
so the argument of this parameter here.
And this is the column name so don't
confuse this with this. Column name,
function, parameter. And don't forget the
comma here and yeah that's basically it.
Let's save this script now and let's
execute it. We assert some data there.
Let's say "The sun" this time, and so
we'd have "The sea", "The sea" again, "The earth",
and "The sun", so I'd like to delete
"The earth" and I would want to put them in
here, delete, so Earth has an ID of 3 so we
would want to pass 3 here, and then
we would view all the current records
once we have deleted them.
Alright, so here are our records and the
Earth has disappeared, so it's working great.
Again as I said this ID will be
extracted from the tuple, so the tuple
will have the ID as the first item and
so basically we'll get from tuple get
the icon with index 0 and we'll pass
that first item to this delete function.
Great, last function would be update.
Update and again how would you want to
update our records? So how the user wants to
update the records? Well again they may
expect to select row from the list box
from the tkinter list box. The values of
that row would display in the entry widgets.
And that from where the user may want to
change one of those cells, of those
entries and press the update button,
so again we will get the selection from the
list box and then we would refer to the ID.
So I did here as the first parameter, but
we would also want to get the new values
that the user would want from those
entries, so let's say the user wanted to
change the title from "The Sun" to "The moon"
let's say, and you'd get that title
so the title will be in the entry box
and pass it here.
Same for author, year and ISBN. Alright.
And then you'd want to update your table,
so date table where the ID is equal to this.
Update table with these new values
where ID is equal to this. First of all
we need to get all these rows, alright.
So update book and you say set, so the
keyword set. Title equal to question mark.
Same, year question mark and ISBN equals
to question mark.
So update book and set these values
where ID is equal to another question
mark, so then we pass the tuple here,
so ID, title, author, and ISBN.
So it's looking good. We commit
the changes and we close the connection.
And let's see how this goes.
So currently we have these rows in the
table, "The see", "The see" again, "The Sun".
So I'd want to comment this out first
and also delete, so let's focus on the
update function, and update so you would
want to pass the ID of the row so that
you want to update, and then you want to
pass the values in the correct order.
So what you want for the new title? Let's
say you "The moon" and then in the real
interface, in the graphical user
interface if the user wants to change
only the title, he'll leave the other
values as they are, so the these values
would be replaced to the existing values.
So John Smith and Year 1918, the
ISBN number, but in this case we are just
in a test mode so we can pass
these values. Smooth, alright.
And a number, so let's see how
these goes now, and it seems it didn't work.
"The Sun" is still there so let's
see what we got here. Update title, author,
year, ISBN where ID is, so the ID
should be at the end of the tuple here.
Because you know we put them in the
correct order that we have set here.
So let's try this out again. Now it's
working, so the ID 4 was replaced to
"The moon", John Smooth and the other values.
Great, so I think we have the backend
script ready.
And what we need now is to attach all these
functions to our buttons, so we still
have work to do, and we'll do that
in the next lecture.