Hey, welcome again and this is the final
push that we will give to our
application, so by the end of this
lecture you'll have a fully working
program that can store and retrieve book
records in an SQLite database. So as you
know we have two scripts, we have
frontend.py and we have
the backend.py script.
We are completely done with a backend.py
script, so we have built all of our
functions that connect to the database
insert, view, search, and delete, and update
data, and now we need to go to the
frontend script because we need to
tweak it a little bit so that the
frontend scrip is able to fetch, to get
data from the backend script, or more
specifically is able to get the function
outputs which are basically tuples of
data, and then insert those tuples of
data in the list box. So basically the
user presses the bottom and then these
functions are triggered and the data are
inserted to the list box. So let's start
from the easiest things, and the first
thing I would like to implement is to
get the records in the list box when the
user presses the view all button. First
of all as I mentioned before you need to
import the backend script in here so that
you are later able to refer to your
functions as something like backend dot
view for example for the database view
function. Now I have been mentioning that
to attach a function to a button you
need to go to where you have defined the
button so to the button function and
then you add a command here, so command
and then goes, here goes the function.
Now if we just call the view function of the
backend script, so if we do backend dot
view, all we are doing is just
executing the view function so we aren't
inserting any data to the list box.
So what we want to do is have another
function and have that function grab the
data from the view function,
and insert those data to the list box.
For example let's call
that function view command, just like that.
Remember you don't pass brackets here
because if you do when you execute
the script this function here if you do
like this this function will be executed
when Python reads your script, but you
don't want that. You want that when
you press the button when the user
presses the button. This function is
executed so the tkinter knows that and if
you just pass this like this, Python tkinter
will execute it when the button is pressed.
So view command and now you need
a view command function, so let's write
our functions just here. Def view command.
So think about the output now. The output
we are getting is tuple, so I'm going to
execute the view function here, so print
view just to see what we have if you
have forgotten it. So Python backend.py,
and so we have actually we have
a list of tuples, so tuples inside the
list and what we want to do now is to
insert each of these tuples, so each of
these database rows as a new row
inside the list, inside the list box.
So what we can do is we can iterate through
this tuple, so that would be for row
in backend.view. So this
is actually this list here, so this is
actually an object, a list object.
Then at list1. I believe that's how
our list box is called. Yeah,
so it's list1 as a variable holding
our list box, dot insert.
Then the insert method gets two arguments.
The first argument is the index where
you want to insert your values. So you
have a list box and that list box has
several places, so it has the first
place and then the second, third and so on.
So if you want to put it in the first
place you do enter zero. If you want to
put it in the second you'd enter an index
of one here one here, and so on.
But the thing about that we are iterating
through these tuples, so we go to the
first tuple and then we would want to
put it, and we would want to put this
tuple as the first item of the list, then
we would want the second to be put as
second item, and so on, so in such cases
the insert method also has a special
index that is called end and then you
pass the row, so what that means is that
the new rows will be put at the end of the
list box. So you have this row and this
is this is put as the first one, and then
this will be put at the end of the existing
rows, so that ensures that every new row
is inserted at the end of the list box.
So I hope that is clear and I
would actually like to execute the
script, so now we have the frontend.py.
And I've made an error here,
so actually I want to import backend
here like that, execute again and we got
the interface, so let's see what view all has.
Name backend is not defined in
line 5, so back, yeah of course it's
not defined because I have a typo here.
Backend, all right. Let's try it again.
Close it.
Let's see, great, so we got the rows
displayed in the list box, but when
you press it again, and again, and again,
and again these rows would be appended
to the existing ones, so we need to
think about how we can actually have an
empty list box when we press the button.
That's actually very easy to do. We need
to ensure here that when these lines are
executed, the list box is already empty.
So what we can do is list one delete.
And 0 end ensure that the you are
deleting everything from the index
of zero, from the row with index of zero to
the end, to the last row.
So let's see how that goes.
View all and if you press you all again,
view again, you always get all the rows
that you have in the database, in the table.
Great, let's now go ahead and define
a similar function for the search entry
button, so the button is this one here,
search entry and again we want the user
to enter at least one value in the
entries, in the entry boxes and then they
press the search entry button, and then
they expect the program to return the
rows that contain the entry that the
user input in the entry box. So again
you'd want to insert data in the list box,
so again you can just call the
search function of the back end script
in here, command, so you need a wrapper
function, so let's say search command.
Another good reason that you want to use
these wrapper functions so to say is
that in some cases like this one here, you
are passing some parameters to the
function, so if you look at the back end
and the view function didn't have any
parameters but the search function
has some parameters,
so that means you're not allowed
to put brackets here, so you have to use
another function where you call your
main backend search function with
parameters actually, and that's what we
are going to do now, so def search command
and again the search command what we
actually get as argument is a title that
the user will input, an author name
a year, and ISBN number. Now the way we're
going to get these parameters is from the
entry widgets, so where is the entry
entry, entry? Here are the entry widgets,
and if you remember that we have this
string van object here and this variable
that has the strings var data type will
be given a value the text
or the number that the user enters in
the entry widget, so keep that in mind.
Let's go ahead here and the first
thing you want to do is list1.delete,
so you want to empty the list, alright.
And then you need to loop through
the backend list output because you
know in this case let's execute this
quickly, so the backend script, so we are
searching for the author name John Smith.
Backend.py.
Alright, we don't have any John Smith at
the moment, so let's look for John Smooth,
so we got an empty list there, save again.
And you'll see that we got a list of tuples,
so in this case we have only one tuple,
but you get the idea.
That means we need to iterate through.
For row again in backend dot search,
and here you need to be careful so the
search function has parameters and the
first parameter will be title text,
so the text that the user
is inputting in the entry widget,
in the text entry widget, however we are
not done because the title text is
actually a string var object, so it's not
a plain string and what we need to do is
actually append a get method here and this
will output a string object, so if the user
enters John Smooth there, in the widget,
this will produce a simple John Smooth string.
So I hope that makes sense.
Author text again, get method. Then we
have year text dot get, and lastly ISBN
text dot get. So for row in the list
that the search function will output for
us when it searches the database
we simply want to insert new values at
the end of the list, just like that.
I can see the syntax highlighting is not
working here, so I probably have some
sort of typo. I'm missing a colon here.
So now for and in were colored in purple.
Okay so let's try out the frontend
script, and let's look for author John Smooth.
Well obviously I pressed the view all
button so I got everything here.
So you want to press search button, alright?
Search, search and it only shows
John Smooth.
If you say view all, it shows everything.
So it seems to be working, and next is
add entry button, so when a user presses
add entry button they expect that the
data they have been typing in the four
entry widgets, these data will be stored
in somewhere.
They don't know where, but
they're stored somewhere, and they'll
be able to retrieve them, so that means
you need to call the insert function
in here, in the backend script. So this
function will get these four arguments,
so the values from the entry widgets and it
will pose them in the book table, as easy
as that, so first thing we might want to
do is go to the add entry button, so here
and then add a wrapper function here.
Add command, and then we create an add
command function. And this is quite
straightforward actually. You just say
backend dot insert and here pass
these values, so I'll just copy this and
paste them here, so let's try this out.
Let's try to add some entries. Let's say
Trees and Grass. Let's say Ben Sand, year
1917 and just put a number there for the
ISBN, and add entry. So the entry has
probably been added to his database, but
we didn't see anything, and you can see it
with the view all function probably, so if
I press view all I will see "Trees and Grass",
but it would be good that when we add entry,
this entry, the new entry is
displayed here so that the user knows
that the entry was successfully added to
the database. So here is "Trees and Grass".
And so let's go ahead and do something
that the entry is shown
in the list box when
user presence add entry, and what we can
do is we first need to ensure that the
list is empty, so delete zero to end,
and the list, and that gives us an empty list.
Then we insert new values
at the end of the list.
So what values? Well these ones,
so the values that the user will enter.
Just like that. So let's see how this goes.
I say "Grasslands", let's say Kirk Hammett
and yea 1910, and a number there.
And this is not quite what we were expecting
actually and we got this because we are
inserting here many values indeed, so we
are telling Python to insert all these
in any new value, these based in a new one
and this as well and so on so forth.
So the solution here is simple just put it as
a single value, so as a tuple and then run
the program again. We have an error here.
So we need one more bracket because this
bracket here closes here,
so just like that.
Try it out again. Let's say "Wonderlands".
Helena Gomez, 1944 and a number here.
Add entry and now we have the row in
one single line. View all.
"Wonderlands" is there. "Grasslands"
is also there, so let's move on.