Okay, we have some more code to go. We
have defined the view, the search, and the add
buttons, so now we have the delete,
the update, and the close button, and I would
like to continue with the delete button
because the delete button is easier to
implement than the update button, so let me
call the interface again. And again think
about the user, and what will user might
expect is they may want to delete
one of the rows. Let's say this row.
So they expect to select this row,
and then they press the delete
selected button
and this row will disappear from the
database, and they may also want to when they
select row they may also want to see
the data in these entries. And we will
take care of that too, so we will fill
these entries with the corresponding
values when the user clicks one of the
rows here. Alright, that makes sense I
believe. And now let's look at the delete
function in the backend script, so what
delete does is it expects for an ID,
the ID of the row, and then this SQL
statement then looks for this ID and
deletes the entire row of the book table
where the ID is equal to this given ID
here, so what we need to do is when the
user selects one of the rows in the
list box, we need to grab the ID of that
row and then that send back ID to the delete
function over the backend script.
And then the delete function takes care
of the row. Oh good, and again in this
case you do also want to append some
sort of delete command function to the,
here, to the delete button, but in this
case I would actually like to do
a button-up approach, so let's first think
of how we're going to get the row
selected by the user.
So let's think about that first, and you
don't know probably, but there is a method
called bind of the tkinter library and
bind is used to bind a function
to a widget event. So let me write the bind
method, so that you understand things
better, so we all we are binding a method
here to the list box widget, so it makes
sense to write that method after way we
have defined the list widget, so we
define this widget here and we configure
it and then list1 dot bind and
the bind method that takes two arguments.
So it takes the event type and
also it takes the function that you want
to bind to the event type. And the event
type here actually goes inside these
characters and it's called ListboxSelect.
And then you want to specify a function
here that returns a list object
with the selection, so something like this.
Actually we will expect a tuple in
this case, a tuple with the ID, the title,
the author, and the year, and the ISBN
number, so let's call that function
get selected row. Okay, and then we go
ahead and define that function.
Let's define it in the very beginning here.
So def get selected row and this function now
because we have bind it to an event,
to a widget event, this function gets
a special parameter called event, and the
event parameter holds the information
about the type of the event.
So Python knows that when you pass these
to the bind method it expects the
function to have this event parameter.
Then, so again this function will return the
tuple, the selected tuple, but first of
all the way this works is that we
first need to get the index of the list
from the list box. You know the list may have
let's say 10 rows and the first row
will have an index of 0, the second an index
of 1 and so on up to 9 if we have 10 rows.
So to get the index of the selected
row of the list box we refer to the listbox,
and then to the cur selection method
of the list box, all right, and I
would actually like to just make a
a temporary return of the index here so that
you see what this object is, and how it
looks like. So let's hope this will work!
It should work.
Python frontend, yeah and so view all.
Actually we should have printed out
the index here. We are just returning it,
so print index and let's try this out again.
So I expect to print other index here.
Yeah, so this is the index of the
selected row, so this is row 1, sorry 0
with index 0, 1, 2 and so on. However as you
see this is not a plain normal, this is
actually a tuple, a tuple with one item.
So what we need to do is a very simple
trick, and we just grab the item with
index 0 of the tuple which is number 2
in this case,
0 in this case, and so on and then we
might try this again. View all.
And now we get single numbers. Great, so
we're very close but not there yet
because we need to get the actual tuple
with all the values of the row and to
get that you need to apply another
method called get, so let's say
a selected tuple, so the actual tuple
that we want, the actual row
that we want is equal to list1 dot get
index, so you can read it like this.
From the listbox get the tuple
with index x and then we can try this
out so what are we getting here?
Don't get confused with this row, this
is being printed out because in the
backend script we actually have a search
function being printed out, so this is
printing the output of the search
function, so this function is saying give
me the row with John Smith as author
name, and next time this will not be
executed, so back. What we want to do is
select a row and we get the row printed
out there as a tuple, so that is great.
So what's next? Well next is we need to pass
the ID of the selected tuple to the
delete function of the backend script.
we go to the delete selected button.
Command equals delete command. That's how
I'm gonna call the script, and that
should be oh here. Def delete command.
And what we have here is backend dot
delete, and again the delete method gets
as argument the ID, so we have a tuple
called get selected row, so we need to
return, return the selected tuple so if
we call the function now get selected row.
Selected row, and we need the item
with index 0 from the get selected row.
So save the script. And we got an error
at line 24. I don't have the colon here.
Try out again. View and let's try to delete
"The Moon", delete and Python is saying that
get selected row is missing one
required positional argument and that's
the event argument, and so python is right
because here we have an event parameter,
so we need to pass that as an argument.
But here we are calling the function
without any argument, so we're getting an
error, on the other and we cannot remove
this event because this function is also
being executed by the bind method so in
that case the hero of the day here would
be a global variable, so you might
already know that local variables like
the selected tuple is a local
variable because it's defined inside
a function, so if you print this tuple
outside the function select a tuple, you'll
get an error because Python will say
sorry I don't recognize this. This is an
undefined object because local variables
make sense only inside the function, so in
that case we can use global variables,
and the way to create a global variable
is by using the global keyword and then
declaring the name of the variable that
you want to create, so in that case if
you print out the selected tuple outside
the function, you'll get the value of the
selected tuple, and the value of the
selected tuple in this case it would be
the tuple with the values of the row.
So in that case we don't need to return the
selected tuple because we can simply
point to the selected tuple variable in
that case, and we need to fix our delete
function here. So we want selected tuple.
And we want the item with index 0 from
the selected tuple, so let's execute again.
View all and let's delete "The Moon".
Delete selected, view all and "The Moon"
is gone, so it seems to be working.
Now I'd also want to fill the entries
with a selected tuple or row if you like.
So we need to use the insert function
of the entry widget, and we could actually
write those methods inside the get selected
row function because you know when
the user clicks one of the rows, when they
select one of the rows we immediately
want to fill those entries with values.
And the first would be the title
and we want to make sure the entry is
empty, so delete 0 to end, delete
everything from the entry if there is
something, and then e1 insert. So what we
want to insert in the author entry?
Well that would be the selected tuple
with the index of 1, so the ID has an index
of 0, the title has an index of 1.
And this would be the same for the other
entries as well, so we have e1, e2, e3, and e4.
And then here we want to grab the author name.
Here we want the year, and the
ISBN number in here. Great, so I hope this
will work. It should work, so view all
select something and insert method
is missing one required argument.
I think I forgot to put where I want to
insert the new values, so we need to end
here, here, here and here. So let's see
again. View all, and now it seems to be
working, so "Trees and Grass", Ben Sand
and so on, and let me try to delete this.
Delete, view all, and the entry is gone.
Great, so now let's go ahead without wasting
any time. Let's go ahead and implement
the update function so back to our backend
script. The update function gets an ID,
and title, author, year, and ISBN.
So unlike the delete function which only
got one item. This gets four items, five
items actually, so in the delete command
function we pass the selected tuple
with an index of 0. Now the update
function will be similar, similar structure
but then we will have multiple
arguments here, so we have ID title,
author, year and ISBN, so selected tuple
with an index of one. Selected tuple with
an index of two. Selected tuple with an
index of three, and selected tuple with
an index of 4, and then we need to add
that function to the update button.
So update command, alright, and I forgot to
change this. Update command. This should
work, so let's see. I've forgotten to pass
the name of the parameter here.
So command equals update command, save and
execute again and view all. Let's try to
update this row, so let's say nine, and
you press update selected and yet
another error. Don't get scared about
errors, the more errors you see, the more
familiar you will become with Python.
It's important to focus on the error to see
what line you're getting the error and try
to understand what type of the error, and the
message you're getting. So in this case
this say delete takes one positional
argument, but five were given.
We didn't execute a delete function here.
we executed the update button which gets
an update command function, and you go to
the update command, so the update command.
Backend delete. That's why we are
getting this error, the update command
is actually executing the delete
method of the backend script, so we want
update instead of delete.
And save the script and execute again.
View all. I want to really update this
number here, so 9 update selected, view all.
And it's not working, and in this case
we're not even getting an error here so
you may feel lost at the moment, so what
you could do in this case is check what you
are returning in your update command
function, so you know that you can
isolate problems by using print
statements, so let's say you want to
check what you are sending to the update
function. I know the problem here,
but just to show you the way you can
troubleshoot things, so print out and
execute this again. View all, get this
"Grasslands", update selected and you
see that the tuple is being printed out
as it is, so this number is not changing.
Actually I didn't change it, so let me
change this again. Let's say 24 and
update selected and so you see that the
number 24 is not being printed out here,
so that means we are sending to the
database this record again, so we're not
sending the updated record. So why is that?
If you have already found it from
earlier when I have an arrow this
function, that's very great.
If you haven't well the reason is that
we are sending to the update method the
selected tuple, and the selected tuple is
the one that the user has selected,
so it's not the actual entry that the
user is sending to the update command,
so in that case we actually want to send
out these values, so the current values
of the entries,
so I'll copy this and paste it just here.
Okay, and the first selected tuple is
the ID, so we want to keep the ID of
the selected row because the user is
changing the other values, not the ID.
And this looks fine, The bracket closes here.
Save so delete this one,
save, execute again.
View all, go to this and let's say 3.
Update selected, view all and 3 is there.
Delete, view all, it goes away.
You can add it again because you have it
in your entries. Add entry and it was added
again and you can see it here.
So everything is working great, and we
want to close this program but the close
button is not working at the moment,
so let's go ahead and implement
that as well, and that's very
straightforward, you just go here and
command equals to. So you want to destroy
the window, right? So window dot destroy.
That's it.
Save the script, try it out. So all these
are working as usual. Close and the
window closes, and you may also want to
put a title to your window, and you use the
WM title method of the window object.
Title and let's say
book store, and you should see
that name in the title bar, so finally
we are done with this program, and I know
there might be things to improve and
I would welcome any suggestions from you
so that we could improve the program.
Programs have versions, so this is
version zero you could say, and I hope you
found this very useful and learned a lot
from this, so I'll talk to you later.