Hi again, so we have this great program
that works very well, and it consists of
three files.
So two Python files, and one dot db file
where the data is stored. This is good.
We can execute the script like this,
so using Python and we get the program
displayed, but think if you want to
give your program to someone else, you
can just tell them install Python and
you can execute the program by going to
the terminal and invoking platform and
the script, so that may get terribly
difficult for users who are not
experienced with programming so in
that case you want to make a standalone
executable program that you can just send
to anyone and they can just double click
it and go ahead and insert data and
retrieve data and so on. So in this
lecture I'll show you how to make an
executable file and you'll make that file
whether you are on a Mac, or Windows,
or Linux so the code is the same.
There exists a great library to make
standalone executables. That is the
pyinstaller, so you can install
pyinstaller using pip.
And now it's terribly easy to make a
standalone executable file out of your
Python scripts. All you have to do is
call pyinstaller, and then point to your
script, so in this case our main script
is frontend.py, so that's the script
that is holding all the code and
it also imports the backend script,
so we want to point to that file, and if you
leave it like this, you'll get a dot exe file
if you are on Windows, a dot app file
if you are on a Mac, and together with
those files you will also get a bunch of
other files that are associated with
your program. The benefit of that is that
it gets easier to troubleshoot any
errors that you may get, so you have
lots of files and then you can go to
those files and find the error, and so on.
But if you want to be practical you'd
want to pass a parameter here called onefile.
So that will create a single
executable file for you, and in this form
you will also get a terminal, a command
line displayed on the background of
your graphical user interface,
so if you don't want that
you can specify another parameter called
windowed, so like that and execute.
You'll have to wait a while and my
executable was created, so if you we're
on a Mac this would be a dot app file,
so mine is here the dist folder, so in this
folder, I can look up here. So frontend.exe.
If you execute that you'll get the
window and as you see you also got the
books.db file generated so by
default this only creates executable files,
and then when you execute the program
for first time, remember that we had
the connect function in the
back-end script so that function creates
a database.
So that's what this did and if you view
all now you don't have any rows, so you
don't have any data because this was
created from scratch.Sso in case you want
to have the existing database, you'd want
to give to your user both
the executable file and the existing
database that you have. So for instance
let's say this doesn't exist and I can
go to my existing database, and if I put
it here so Python knows where to search
for the database.
Now if you view all you gather data from
the existing database and we can make a quick test.
Let's add the book. "The great shirt".
Andi Taylor, and year 1913 and put a number
there, add entry and the entry is added
to the database, and you can close the
program and that's it. Hope you enjoyed this!
I'll see you in the next lecture.