Hey welcome to this new section and
throughout the lectures of this section
you are going to learn computer
vision with. Python I'll explain computer
vision in a minute. So that's what we're
going to learn in this section
and then in the next section we'll build
an application that detects moving objects
from the computer webcam and stores
and visualizes the times when the object
entered and exited the video frame.
So that's an application area of
computer vision. Now, maybe you have an
idea of what computer vision is, but if
not I'll explain it now. So computer
vision is the field that deals with
acquiring and processing images and it
makes decisions based on the, on the
images, so you pass an image to the
computer and the computer tries to understand
it and it can do certain things such as
it can tell you how many faces
there are in the image, and what
color dominates the image and so on.
Now, computers are dumb. I mean you
have to tell them what to do exactly.
That's where Python comes in. We'll use
Python to load images and process them,
and do things like phase and motion
detection. Now vision includes both
images and videos because videos are
simply stacks of images that show very
fast. So computers and therefore Python
use the same commands to read images and
videos and you can do computer vision
with Python using OpenCV. OpenCV stands
for open source computer vision and
is a library used not only in
Python, but in other programming
languages as well to do computer vision
tasks. So in this section I will
introduce it to OpenCV and you will
learn how to use it by detecting faces
from images. And then in the next section
we'll dive deeper and
process videos with OpenCV and detect
moving objects in real time webcam video.
So yeah, that's about this lecture and
let's move on and quickly set up OpenCV
in the next lecture, and then work with it
after that. So yeah, thanks
and see you in the next lecture.