Great, so let's go ahead and play around
with OpenCV a little bit. Specifically
what you'll learn in this lecture is
you will learn how to load images in Python
using OpenCV. You'll learn how to display
them, resize, and then save the resized
images in new images image files, so load
display, resize, and write images.
And I've got a nice image here of a galaxy,
so I'll play around with this. The first
thing you want to do is import the
library, and then the second thing is you
want to load the image in Python so
image would be equal to cv2.image
read method, so the method expects now
the path to the image that you want to
load in Python and that would be galaxy.jpg.
So I, my script1.py file
file is in the same directory with
galaxy.jpg, so i just need to pass
the file name here. And then there is yet
another parameter for image read,
for imread method and then this parameter
takes three arguments. Now, this parameter
specifies how you want to read the image
in Python so do you want to read it as
our RBG image which means you want
three bands in your image,
so you want a color image with
a red band, blue, and green band. So if you
want to read the image as it is, so with
colors you'd want to pass one here.
If you want to read the image as black and
white image, so in a grayscale you'd want
to pass zero, and having a grayscale image
implies that your image will have one
band and I'll get back to bands and
explain them in just a moment. So we
also have minus one. This means the color
image, but you also have an alpha channel
which means your image will have
transparency capabilities, so if you
apply operations that require
transparency
you can do that when you read, when you
load the image with a minus one argument here.
Okay, so I would like to try out 0.
Great, now before I show the image, before
I display the image on the screen I'll
like you to understand what this image
object is about, so I'd want to print the
type of it, just like that. Execute the
script, script1, yeah.
Of course and try again, so this is a Numpy N
dimensional array, and if you want you
can print that out, and you'll see the
actual Numpy array so this is a
two-dimensional array with values in the
horizontal axis and in a vertical axis
as well. So think of the image now and
this would be the very first, so the top
left intensity value of the first pixel.
So 14 for example would be the intensity
value in the grayscale for the first
pixel of image so for the top left pixel
of the image, and then for the second
pixel and so on and then you have these
dots which means Python cannot display
ever listed a long list in here because
you have a couple of thousands of values
in the first row, and then you have a
second row of pixels in the image
and the third and so on, and this makes
the matrix of the pixel image, and if
you want to know how many numbers how
many values you have in the horizontal
direction, how many values you have in
the vertical direction you can go ahead
and print image shape. Okay. So let's say
that the image resolution
is 1485 by 990.
So Python stores the image as a Numpy
array, as a matrix of numbers as easy
as that. If you want to check the
dimensional of your array, of your image you
can do that with this expression and you
see that you have two dimensions. Now if
they sauce a color image so with three
bands, red, blue, and green things
will change a little bit.
So you've got three dimensions and you
also see that the new array is a bit
different, so here you've got values for
each of the band so for green, to red
green, and blue, so I'd like to stick with
the gray image, and what I can do now is
I can display the image on the screen
and for that you want to use the image so
imshow method and this will display a
window and you want to name that window,
so you want to put a title for that window.
Let's say galaxy. What you pass here
is the image object, so this one. Great.
And then what you want to do is you want
to specify a time for your window
to be closed because this will show the
window but you also want to define some
functionalities so that the user can
close the window. If you put 0 here
when the user presses any button, the window
will close. Let me change this to cv2.
So if you put 0, the user can
close the window pressing any button.
If you want to put a time you could say
2 000 and that implies 2 000 milliseconds,
so that means 2 seconds. So we said how
the user wants to close the window and
then you want to specify what to do when
the user presses a button or waits for
2 seconds, so we want to destroy all windows.
That's the method that closes the window.
Good, let's see what will happen.
Okay so we got the image displayed and
it waited for two seconds and then it closed.
If you put it at zero the image
will stay there, and if you press the
button it will close. And let me show the
image again. Now the reason that you
don't see the image fit on my screen is
that the image as you see in these values
is 1,485 pixels high so the height, this
is the height and it's 990 pixels wide.
So my screen resolution is set at 1280
by 720, so that means that this image
with this size doesn't fit on my screen
because my screen is too small for this.
So in this case, let me close this.
What you can do is you want to resize
the image and then show the resized image.
So we load the image and before showing
it, before passing it to the imshow
method you want to say let's say resized
image. That will be equal to cv2.resize.
And this would get two parameters,
so the first is of course is the image
object that you want to resize, so img is
our variable, and then you want to
specify a tuple with the new dimensions.
I'll say 1,000 by 500 and then you want
to pass the new image here, so what's
happening here is that Python is
actually resizing the Numpy array,
so it will take the array with this
number of pixels, number of values
and it will create an array
with these new dimensions, so what will
happen there is that Python will
interpolate those values, so it has quite
a lot of values here but then it goes
from this to this, so when it sees let's
say it has 4 for one value and then six
for the neighbor value, and what Python
will do is that it will get 4 and 6
basically, and it will just make a value
out of it, so let's say five, that's
basically the idea, so it interpolates
the values, and then it shows the
interpolated image on the screen which
looks pretty nice in our eyes. Okay,
let's see this. And this is the image.
And you see that this is quite stretched
a little bit, so it was a tall image,
but now it's quite wide, and because
this is actually the width of the image
and this is the height, so if you want
you can see 500 and 1000. Save again.
And now you see more or less the true ratio
of the image, but if you want to keep the
ratio of the image you'd want to go more
advanced here, so let's say from this,
so let's say we would want to show a size
that is half of this so that that would
keep the ratio of the image. So what we
can do is we need to access to these
values, and we can grab those values
form the shape, the method, so this produces
a tuple with these two values, and then we
go here and say image shape, and this
would be this value, so 990 which has
an index of 1, and then we have again
image dot shape with index of 0
for this number.
And then we want to divide this by two.
Okay, and I expect to get an error from
this, but let's see, so yeah we've got
an error. It's a type error. Integer argument
expected got float, but here, what we're
doing here is that when we divide this
number by two we will get a float, so we
would get something
like 742.5
In that case what you want to do is
convert this to an integer, so 742.5
becomes 742, okay and let's keep
the consistency, so integers and for
this as well. Let's see! We've got
an invalid syntax here, so it points us to
line 11 somewhere in the beginning which
can be quite misleading, so you want to
see before that line which is here and
you can see that this bracket here
close is here, so we need another bracket
which closes in the first bracket here.
So save that, try again and this time the
image looks good. So you'll learn how to
load an image in Python, and you'll learn
how to resize an image, how to show an
image on the screen and now let's go
ahead and write the resized image in a
new file. For that you'd want to use the
imwrite method, so image write and
you want to give a name to a new image.
Galaxy let's say resized dot jpg and
then you pass the image object that you
want to store in this file.
So the comma goes also here and the
image you want the store is resized image.
That's it. Execute and we got the
old image resize on the fly, so Python
gets a Numpy array, it interpolates it,
so it resizes it and then it shows it on
the screen, so this is galaxy this one here.
And then we can close this and here
we've got our new image, so galaxy resized.
So if you go to the folder where these
files are, you'll see that this image
has new dimensions, so 495 by 742.
And that's what I wanted to teach you
in this lecture.
Hope you enjoyed it and talk to you later.