Well I hope you solved the exercise and
I believe it was not a difficult one.
My purpose there was to get you used to
it with the OpenCV code, and also why
not to practice the For Loop, so as you
can imagine this exercise would be solved
by using a For Loop, so let me go
through the code line by line quickly.
So we have to import OpenCV, so cv2 and
the glob library if you can recall it
what the globe does is that it finds
the path names of some files given a certain
pattern, so in this case for instance I
have this JPG files here, so, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
images and I said ok, create a list of
file names that contain everything in
first part and then jpg as the extension.
So that will create a list such as say like
C and then path here and then galaxy, the
jpg and then the other image path and so on.
You get the idea. And then what we need to
do is iterate through this list. For each
path image path in in the list, in this
list, we'll do these operations for each
of these items, so first we we'll read
that image path, okay that image file
actually as a black and white image so 0
is the flag, is the argument which implies
an image to read as black and white,
in the grayscale actually, and then we
create a variable where we will store
the resized images, so the image is 100
by 100. So I'm passing the original image
here and the size, the new size that the
image will get. Then we want to show the
image just for demonstration. This is not
really important, but it lets you check
out the images that are being resized.
And this is the name of the window and
then I pass here a wait key method and
500 means 500 milliseconds, so each image
will show and it will wait for half
a second, so 500 milliseconds and then
after this half second, Python will go
to the next line, and then to the
next, and then it will go to the next
item of the list and so on.
So wait key 500 milliseconds and then we
have destroy all windows after this time
passes, and then we write the resized
image so re was a variable that holds
the image object, the resized image object
and this here, all this is the new name of
the file, so what we get here is so we will
have resized in the beginning of the
image name and then just after that
we will have the name of the original
image, so for instance we would have, for
galaxy would have resized galaxy dot jpg.
So image here would be galaxy dot jpg
here which is this one here, and yeah
because the script is inside this folder,
this list actually the image list would
look something like galaxy dot jpg and then
kangaroos in Australia dot jpg and so on.
So this gets the relative paths of the files.
We're not getting the full path. Okay,
I hope that is clear, so resized galaxy.
We could add another score so that
we discriminate the resized word from the
other image name, great. Let me execute this.
Python script, so half a second, half a second,
and it's done. And let's check the images.
So from here up are the original images
and these are the image products, so you
can see here that all these
are 100 by 100,
and they are in a grayscale. Okay.
That's it. See you in the next lecture.