So here we go. I have opened up an Atom
here so I'm going to use Atom to build
the bookstore program so to say.
That uses tkinter and sqlite3 as libraries so
I'll go ahead and create a new Python
file in here. Script1.py.
Now to build graphical user interfaces
with tkinter you need the tkinter library
and you don't have to install it because
tkinter is a built-in Python library.
So all you have to do is go ahead and
import tkinter. If you are on python 2,
this would be with a capital T.
In Python 3 it's tkinter, simply like that.
Good practice however is to actually
import everything from, everything from
tkinter so from tkinter import all. So why
why we do that? We do that because we're
going to use a lot of tkinter
objects in our scripts so it makes sense
to just load them all instead of
referencing them with tkinter.button
for example. Instead of doing that we can
just say button and then we enter the
parameters and so on.
So let me create a graphical user
interface. Now a tkinter program is made
up of two main things. We have the window
and you have the widget, so for example
the window is all this program here
that you see, and then you have
buttons and things like that which are
called widgets, so first of all you need
to create the window, and I like to call
my variable window and that would be
equal to tk. That's it. That would create
an empty window for us, but we need to do
something more here. We say window.mainloop.
This is always necessary.
So we open the window, we create a window
and then everything goes between these
two lines, so you create widgets between
these two, and this is necessary because if
you don't have these, your program will open
up and it will close in a split of a second.
So basically this allows you
to actually press that X button
on the corner of a window and cause the
program, so this should be always at the
end of your code. Now I'll save this
script and going to execute it.
And we got an error it says tkinter, tk is not
defined, so python is not recognizing
this function here because it should be
capital T. And execute again. And this is
the window and it has nothing inside,
so let go ahead and add a button.
So we store the main window in a variable
and we're going to do the same for
widgets so we're going to create variables.
Let's say b1 equals to button.
So the button is a function that
generates a button widget.
The bottom function takes some arguments.
If you want to get a full list of arguments you
want to do some code introspection.
Let's say iPython here and from tkinter
import all and then let's say button
and a question mark. And here you can see
what parameters you get you can pass
to the button function. Now the very
first parameter you'd want to add to
a widget is the variable of the window,
of the main window, so you need to tell your
widget the window that the widget
has to be packed to.
So window and then you can pass
parameters like the one you see here.
Let's say one of the main parameters
would be text, so text equals let's
say to the string execute.
So that is the text, the label
that will be displayed over the button.
Now if we try to execute this script now
you'll see that we don't have a button
yet and that's because we haven't
specified where to put that button.
To do that you need to use the pack method
which is a widget method and execute
again and now you see the button.
However there is another way to actually put
your widgets in your window. That is
the grid method, grid and often it's
a matter of preference whether to use pack
or grid, but the idea of grid is that
with the grid method you have more control
on the position of your buttons and your
your widgets in general because here you'd
specify the row and the column where
you want to put your button,
so everything starts from 0 and so
the first row it has an index of 0 and the first
column has an index of 0 and so on.
I actually found an illustration for that.
So this is a tkinter program and we
have two rows here, so we have this first row
whiche should have an index of 0 and you
have the second row which should have an
index of the one and you have columns.
So 0 1 2 3 and so on and let's say the ok
button which is this one here would have
a row of 0 1 2 so 2 for the row and
then 0 1 2 3. 3 for the column. Then you
might also have widgets were which span
in more than one row or a column.
In that case you'd add another parameter
here called rowspan and that would be
equal to a number. Let's say if you put 2,
the button would span in two rows.
In our case this is not necessary actually
because we don't have
lots of widgets. We only have one button
and so let me execute this script now
and see what we get. So we get a button
which actually does nothing because
we haven't specified what action to perform
when you're pressing the button and I'll
explain that in the next lecture, but for
now let's add some more widgets here.
Just for you to get more familiar with
widgets. So let's add an entry widget and
let's say a e1 for that, so entry 1
equals to Entry, and then guess what is the
first parameter? And that's the window
parameter, and we can leave it like that for now.
Let's say e1.grid and row,
let's keep it in same row and in column1.
Save, execute and here we have an entry.
So what's an entry, an entry
it's like an area where you can enter
a value and then you can interact with
that value in your script, so let's say you
enter kilometers here and you'd want
to have a button that converts those
kilometers to miles so the button would
get the value of this area here, and it
would display it in another widget which
could be a text widget, so let's add a
text widget. Let's say t1 equals Text
window of course, and let's say
t1 grid row 0 column 2.
That's it, execute and we got a very
big text widget because the default size,
the default height and width is actually
quite a big number, so we need to specify
two parameters for the text widget.
We would need to put the height let's say
one cell and the width.
Let's say 20 and so this is the widget area.
and this is the entry and this is the button.
And that's it for this lecture.
In the next lecture I'll show
you how to put these widgets in life
so that they can actually do something.
See you in the next lecture.