Hi again and in the previous lecture we
built this graphical user interface with
tkinter, but the problem is this does
nothing for now so we press this
but it doesn't do anything, so what
I'd like to do here is, the final output
I'd like to have is when I execute this
button, so we have we have an entry here
we can input a value and I want to
execute this button and get miles here
in the text area, so miles is like one
kilometer unit is equals to one mile
times 1.6, so if I execute this I want
something like 16 here to be generated.
So a very simple program. Note that this
is not one of the real programs that I've
promised to build in this course. So this
is just to get you up and runing with
tkinter, so let's close this now and to
have a button do something we need to
add a command parameter here, so the
command parameter takes a function here
as argument, as a value and then when you
press that's that button, the execute button
in this case, the function that you have
here will be executed. So let's say we
have a function here def kilometers to miles.
Now let's say this function
for now just prints out some text.
Let's say success for instance because
you know it's good to before you write
your actual program it's good to use
print statements to try things out
so that allows you to isolate your problems.
If something happens here you know that
you can have a problem with a print
statement, but if you had more
complicated expression here it gets
harder to know whether the problem
happens in here that you are not
pointing to the correct function or you
have a problem with your statements,
so it's good to use simple statements first
like the print statement.
So you'd go here and
kilometers to miles, that is a function
and one thing you should keep in mind is
that you don't pass the brackets here,
so this is not a usual function call.
You are just referencing to the function here
and let Python take care of the rest.
So the function name goes here and let's
try this out. Execute and you see that
we got success printed out in here
Press again success success success,
so it's working.
However we don't need to print our
success in the command line. We want to
print out a value in the text area.
Now we need to look at the entry widget
because series where we are going to get
the value from, so the user enters a value
in the entry widget and then we
grab that value and then we use that
value in our function and for this there
is a parameter called text variable
and that would be equal to a string object
which we have to declare further
up here, so let's say you want value,
so that's a variable and that'll be equal to
the stringVar function and then we
point to e1 value, a variable which
we have just created so this variable
will get the value depending on what the
user will input in the entry widget.
Then we can use this value whatever we like.
Let's say we want to print that out.
E1 value and then we also need to add
something extra here which is
a get method of the stringVar object,
so this is a special object. Is not a string.
A Python plain string. To get an
actual string from out of this object
we need to apply the get method, so save
this and try the script, let's say 10
here, execute and we get 10 printed out
on the terminal, so we haven't yet
connected this string
here with the text widget so let's do just
that here. The idea here is that we need
to insert a value to the text widget and
to do that what text widget has a method
call insert, so you need to refer to the
text widget that you want. So t1 is our
text object and then apply the insert method.
And the method gets an argument first
which is the place where you want to
insert the text. Let's say we want to
insert at the end of the text widget.
For example let's suppose you are inserting
many lines of text in your widget and
you have to apply to execute this
method multiple times and each time if
you put END, you'd enter the new text
at the bottom of the existing text, so you
are saying put at the end this text.
E1 value.get.
So the string of value that the user
will enter in the entry widget, so let's
see how these goes. Execute the function
and put some text here. You can also put
anything. Hey there. Execute and you get
the string printed out in a text widget.
All right but we don't want to just
grab this value and insert it in the text.
We want to first do something with
this value and then we insert the product,
the output in the text widget so let's
say we will grab the e1 value.get.
And we will multiply that by 1.6
and that would be miles, so miles
equals to the value that the user inputs
times 1.6, so you are asking the user
to input kilometers and 1 mile is equal
to 1 kilometer times 1.6. actually is
something like 1.606, I don't remember
the exact value, but you get the idea.
And lastly you'd want
to pass miles in here, so you want
to insert the miles output value in the widget.
Save and execute and I expect to
get an error here let's say 10.
Yes, we got an error and so when you get errors
don't just try to copy this error and
paste it on Google and try to see what
other people are saying. You may waste a
lot of time. Instead invest some time and
try to understand this error, so what this
is saying is a type error. Can't multiply
sequence by non integer of type float.
So a sequence can be a list, can be a string,
a tuple etc. And Python is trying to
multiple a sequence with a non integer
which is a float, so the float here is the
1.6 number and Python is trying to
multiply 1.6 with a sequence
with this here so this is not a number
because the get method actually grabs
a string out of a stringVar objects and
a string cannot be multiplied with
a float number. If this was 2, it was
possible to multiply for example if you
multiply me, the string me times 2,
you'd get me me, so, but you cannot
multiply me by one point six because
it doesn't makes any sense. Anyway, so a
solution to this is you want to convert
the value that the user inputs
to a float and you do that by adding the
float function, so watch out for the
brackets here. You see there is an
underline under the bracket and you have
an underline here, so this means is bracket
it closes in here, so everything looks fine.
So if we execute again. 10 and execute.
And we get the expected output.
You can delete this print function.
We don't need it anymore, and I believe that
was a good start with
the tkinter library.
And you should not be able to make more
advanced interfaces, however we'll be
building a real advanced graphical user
interface with tkinter which will
interact with a database, so it'll be
real world program, and for now I'll just
hand you an exercise in the next lecture
so that you practice tkinter a little bit,
and you also get to know with some more
cosmetic aspects, so you will make the
problem that we built in this lecture
you'll make it more visually appealing
and you'll make sure you'll get your
hands dirty with tkinter a little bit.
I'll talk to you later