Hi there and I'm glad to introduce you
to this new section of the course, and in
this section you're going to learn how
to interact with databases via Python
and what that means is that you'll use
specific Python libraries, and you're
going to operate a database from Python,
using Python. You're going to do
operations such as inserting data into
the database tables you'll be able to
update data or delete and query data
from the database. And then you are able
to use those data in your Python program.
Python is able to interact with many
databases such as MySQL, PostgreSQL
Oracle, or SQLite etc. In this section
you're going to learn how to interact
with an SQLite database and the
PostgreSQL database as well. SQLite and
PostgreSQL are different in that SQLite
is not a client server database instead
it is embedded into the end program.
So what does that mean? Well let's look at
this program. If you followed the previous
section you know that we're going to
build this program in the next section.
When you click a button here you see
some data and these data are stored in
SQLite database. In contrast to other
databases such as PostgreSQL SQLite is
based on file, so all this data here are
stored in a dot DB file, database file.
So that means you can just give this
this problem to someone else who don't
have SQLite installed and they can use
this program, so they can add more data
here, can update data and you leave them
and so on.
But if you have this program
in a PostgreSQL database, the user you
give the program to they need to have
Postiglione installed in a computer
tobe able to operate the data.
So consider SQLite a small database and
you can call it portable, but it's very
popular and PostgreSQL would be more
appropriate to use in a web application.
So let's say you have some forms you're
getting some data from the user
on your website.
You store your data on a PostgreSQL
database on your server and Python
is the program that gets these data from
your forms on client, on the browser and
sends those data in your database.
Now to be able to interact with these databases
you need to have two libraries and these
libraries serve as interfaces
to actually send SQL code to the database.
And the library to interact with an SQLite
database is called Sqlite3 and the
library to work with a PostgreSQL
database is psycopg2. So in this
section now in the next lecture I'll
show how to work with SQLite 3 and then
we'll jump to psycopg2.
So let's move on.