All right, in this lecture you're going
to learn how to use sqlite3. So sqlite3 is
a Python library to interact with
SQLite databases, so think of it
as a Python wrapper of SQL code, so you can
actually write SQL code inside Python
using sqlite3. You don't need to install
sqlite3 because sqlite3 is
a built-in Python library. So what we have
to do is import sqlite3. And let me test it.
Script1, yeah, it's working.
Now a standard process of interacting with
a database would consist of five steps.
First is you connect to the database
Second is you create a cursor object and
the cursor object is like a pointer to
actually access rows from a table
for database. Then the third step is you
apply an SQL query, so you may want to
insert data in a database or select data
from the table and so on and so forth.
And then the fourth step is you commit
your changes to the database and then
you close the connection, so let's go
ahead and write an example with all
these five steps that I just mentioned.
So the first thing you need to create
a connection and you want to store that
connection object in a variable, so let's
conn that should be equal to sqlite3
dot connect and what you pass
here is the database file, so let's say
lite.db and if you don't have
the database file yet, your database will be
created by this line of code,
and the connection will be established.
If you have a database, a connection will be
established with your existing database.
As simple as that. Then you have to
create a cursor object, so cur,
the variable and you need to refer
to your connection, and then to the
cursor method which is a method of
the connection object. So far so good.
Then here comes the actual SQL code. You want
to point to your cursor object and then
use the execute method, and then inside
brackets is where you enter your SQL code.
Remember your SQL code always goes
inside quotes, so you pass the SQL code
as a string to the execute method of the
cursor object on the sqlite3 library.
So if you're familiar with SQL this should
be easy for you. If you're not familiar
with SQL, SQL is quite simple,
so you'll be able to learn it quite quickly.
So at this point we have a database but
we don't have any tables in the database.
Because you know a database is made of
tables and tables have rows and columns,
so first you want to create a table
and a good practice is to use capital
letters for the SQL keywords, so create
is an SQL keyword and table this is SQL
keywords as well, and then you want to
specify that the name that you want to
give to the table. Let's say store. that's
how you order Python via SQL to create a
table, but then you need to specify what
columns you want, what fields you want in
your table. So let's suppose we are
creating a table. We have a store, we have
a shop and we want to store our products
in a SQLite database table. So we would
want to have the item, so that would be
the item name and the item would be
a text data type. So text is like a string
in Python and then you'd want to have
quantity and that would be an integer.
So how many of these item you have in your
store and the price as well, and let's
say real for price which would be
a float in Python so a decimal point
number and that's it. This closes the quotes
on the SQL code, and here is last
bracket of the execute method.
Then you need to commit these changes
to the database, so you refer to the
connection and commit. And then you want
to close the connection, so that's it.
You save that and go and execute.
Qlite is no defined of course because I
have made an error here, a typo and again.
As you see a database was created.
Now if you run the program again
you get an error because the table
already exists in the database, so what
you would do here is a simple trick.
You need to add some code in your SQL line
line you say. Create table if not exist.
So save and if run your code again
now nothing will happen because what
Python does is it goes and connects to
the database, then it creates a cursor
and then if there is a table called store
it doesn't do anything and it goes
to the next line. If there was no table
it would create a table, so it's good to
have these simple conditional here
inside the SQL code. How about adding
some data to our empty table? Let's try that.
Cur execute, so we are executing
some SQL code again and the keyword that
that is Thursday inserts data
to the database is insert. Then you want to
specify where you want to insert the data.
So insert it to store. And what values you
want to insert through your store table?
So values, then you open brackets and
inside the brackets you enter the values
in the correct order, so in the order
that you have defined your columns
so you'd have item, quantity, and price.
And let's say wine glass. Now this is
a string so it should go inside quotes
and you should use single quotes here
because you're using double quotes for
the alter expression, so if you use double
who's here you will confuse Python and
you'll get an error, so use single quotes.
That's why we have different kinds of
quotes to wrap around strings. So we have
the string Wine Glass and let's say we
have quantity of eight and the price of
10.5. Save that and go ahead and execute.
We didn't get an error so that was successful.
Now what if we want to insert
another row? Well we could add that line
in here under this, but then when we
execute the code we would get this
line executed as well, so we would
have a duplicate of this row, therefore
what we could do in this case is we
would use the function to wrap around our
separate SQL statements. So you can
indent this block of code if you like.
You can go to edit lines, indent, or you
could use the shortcut which can be
specific in your keyboard so just look
here for your shortcut, keyboard shortcut,
and you can just use that. And so the
reason I am intending the block of code
is that I want to create a function here.
Let's say function create table.
Don't forget a colon there. And then I want
a separate function for inserting data.
So that would be the SQL statement for the
insert function, but you can see the
difference between this function and
this function. Here we are not creating a
connection to the database which is wrong.
So you'd want to insert these lines
in here so that you establish
a connection with the database and then
you correctly close that connection.
So you know how to use Python functions now.
And naturally the need comes to pass
parameters to your function here so you'd
want to say item, so just some variables.
Quantity
and price and then you would
want to somehow replace these parameters
in here so that every time you call the
function you insert some arguments and then
those values are inserted to your
table.
Now you can use string placeholders,
Python string placeholders to replace
these values with the values that the user
will pass when they call the function,
but this is not a good practice because
your code would be prone to SQL
injections for mockers and that applies
when of course your web application
is on the web, but anyway
a good practice though is to put
question marks in here and then after the SQL
statement, so after the double quote
you'd want to pass the variables that
this question marks will be replaced with.
So you'd who want item, so in the
correct order, quantity, and price.
So let's try this out now. I would like to
execute the insert function that I just
created with some new items so let's say
water glass, and we have 10 of them.
This would be less expensive. Save that
and go and execute. I made a terrible
error here. I wrapped close all
the arguments, so water glass should be
in quotes and these are numbers, so save
again, try it again. And your data should
be now in the database, so one more
time and let's say coffee cup.
Save, execute again
and now I am sure you would want to see
the data that you have been inserting
in your database, in your table, so let's
create a function that does just that.
Let's say def view and you'd want to
establish a connection with the database,
so let's copy that and paste it here.
And then here goes the SQL code,
so cur execute, so we always use the
execute method to send SQL code
to the database and then we have quotes.
Let's say we want to select the data of
all the columns of the store table.
So select an asterisk which means all from
store, all right. So we selected them but
how do we actually fetch this data so
that we can use them in Python?
Well the way to fetch them is by using the
fetch all method and we want to select,
to store those rows in a variables,
so let's say rows cur fetchall
and then we need to close the connection.
So in contrast to the other methods where we
were writing data to the table, here we
are just selecting data, so we don't have
to use the commit method. And we want to
return the rows variable. And I'd just like
to print out the output of the function.
So the output of the function is the rows
variable, so I'll get the rows value
printed out on the command line. Save the
script, execute. Of course I have a type
here and should be return. Try again.
And here are our data. So we have
wine glass, water glass, and we have two
lines of coffee cups and that's
because we executed the function earlier,
the insert function and then now that
I executed the script again with
a purpose to get the view function
executed, the insert function was
executed as well for the second time.
So coffee cup was inserted two times
in the table. All right, that's for this
lecture, and in our next lecture I'll
show you some more operations you can do
with the database, so talk to you later.