So in the previous lecture I introduced
you to the sqlite3 library and I showed
you how to create a table in your SQLite
database and how to insert data in your
database, and how to select data and view
them in Python, so we have these four
lines for rows in our database table,
and in this lecture I'll quickly show
you how to delete and update data
from your table. So again I'll create
a function, so let me copy this and we
still need to connect to the database
and create a cursor object and then we
need to use the execute method and in
this case I would like to delete
the row that has wine glass, so I inside
execute we would right delete from store
where item equals, I would like to
use a question mark place holder here so
question mark in brackets. We'd want
the parameter that we would pass through
our function, so this item here is the one we
put inside here. Item and let me change
the name of our function. So this is this one.
Don't confuse it with this, this is
the column of our table. This was the
row of our previous function.
Delete this as well and you also want to commit
the changes to your database.
So conn.commit.
So that's it and I'd like to comment
this out, so I don't want to execute
the insert function again, and I want the
view function to be executed after we delete
the row, so delete. So which item,
the row of which item would you want to delete?
So the item wine glass and let's see
what will happen.
And we got an error, an sqlite3 error.
Incorrect number of bindings supplied. Line 28.
So I can see here. There's something I often forget.
You need to add a coma here.
You'll see that way I teach you how to
connect to a PostgreSQL database
and how to query data from a PostgreSQL
database. The code is quite similar but
it has some critical changes like
this one here, so it can be confusing when
you work with different kind of databases.
Let's try this out again and
yeah it seems to be working now.
Wine glass is not here, so that's how you
delete a row. Let's now add another function
for updating data. Update. In this one I
would like to update the quantity or
water glasses, so I'd want to change
this from 10 to 11. Again you establish
a connection to the database,
a cursor object and then you execute
and here you enter the update SQL command.
So update. What you want to update is the
store table and which column do you want
to update from the store table? So you
want to set the name of the column which in
this case would be quantity, and that
would be equal to what? Guess what?
Question mark and then you say where or
let me show you how to update more than
one column, so if you wanted more than
one column you'd use a comma and let's
say price equals another question mark
alright so we say update store and set
quantity and price to these, but which row?
So we need to specify the
conditional here, so where item equals to
wine glass, or you can also set this to a question
mark so you have three placeholders here
and then you have the quote to close
your SQL statement and inside brackets
you want to pass the parameters quantity.
And you have the second one is price and item.
When you have more than one
parameter here you don't put a comma at
the end so all of this adds like this.
And you also want to pass these
parameters here so they reflect your
function input, so what we have here is
we are updating the store table and we
set the value of the quantity column and
append the price column to these values
but only for those rows where the item
will be equal to a given value, so we
give that value to this one here and
the first two to these ones, so you get
the idea.
Save the script and you need to call it here.
So let me comment this alt out and update.
So what quantity do you want to pass?
11 let's say and the price
was five let's say it will go up to six.
And which item you want to update?
Water glass. That's it. Save your script and
try it out. And we got these values
updated as we expected and that's what I
wanted to teach you in this lecture.
It could be more practical to actually
have an ID here so we say quantity and
price where the ID is equal to a number,
so we don't have to pass the entire name
which can be confusing or it's prone to errors.
So in that case we would want
to change the table here and we would
want to add a primary key that auto
increments, but you'll learn how to do that
in the next section
of course, so there I'll show you how to
to make the real world program and we
will implement that in that program.
So these were some trivial examples and you
get a much better idea
in the next session so next we will jump
to PostgreSQL and we'll work with the
psycopg2 library. Talk to you later.