Welcome to this lecture! We are done with
sqlite3 so I hope you were able to build
this script that I showed you throughout
the previous lectures because in
this lecture we are going to use the
script but I'll modify it, so that it is
compatible, interactive with
PostgreSQL databases so luckily most of
the code is the same with other with some
slight changes. Of course we would need
another library called psycopg2 and then
we will grab methods from that library
and unlike sqlite3 psycopg2 needs
to be installed, so it's a third-party
library, it don't come as sub built-in
Python library, so you need psycho PG 2
installed and you also need PostgreSQL
installed in your computer. So in this
lecture I would like to show you how to
install PostgreSQL and psycopg2 as well.
Alright, this is the official web
page of PostgreSQL and you can just go
to downloads, just here or down here, and then
you want to find your operating system,
so PostgreSQL works on Mac, Linux
and Windows.
Solaris as well. So I'm on Windows.
I'll just click on windows and when you
install PostgreSQL you are also
installing the pgAdmin3 which is
a graphical tool where you can see your
databases. If you're familiar with MySQL,
pgAdmin is equivalent to PHPMyAdmin.
POstgreSQL also comes with a Stack
Builder which is a package that you can
use to download and install other
extensions, PostgreSQL extensions, so let's
say you want an extension for spatial
data so to store spatial data in PostgreSQL
so that you can use it for GIS
applications, so that's an extension for
that called PostGIS.
So anyway I'll show you
to install extensions. First you need to
download PostgreSQL and I am on a Windows
so I would click this and I'll wait a while
until my download finishes.
So I'll quickly go through the
installation process. So I'm just being
asked where I want to install PostgreSQL
and where my data will be stored and
here it should be careful with this
credentials so your Super User, the ones
who have most of the privileges to your
databases and your super user name is
Postgres and I'd actually like to create
a simple file, a text file just to store
my credentials. I would like to say the
password as well.
One, two, three, all right. So I'll enter
postgres1234 password.
Next and this is the port of your
server, of your database server so
I'd want to take a note of this too.
This is a about your local settings so I'll
just leave this default and you'll just
have to wait a while until the isolation finishes.
All right, that was successful.
Now if you want to launch Stack Builder
to install extensions for the PostgreSQL
database, you may want to have this checked.
So this is my database server
and here you have a bunch of extensions
that you may want to install.
For example spatial extensions and you
have PostGIS for 32-bit
and PostGIS for 64-bit.
If I click Next this tells me that
I need one package at least to be
installed, so let me just install PostGIS.
All right, I agreed to the PostGIS license and
then just go next.
This is asking me about Gdal which is
another interface for GIS data.
All right that was how to install external
extensions. If you want to go back to
Stack Builder later your Stack Builder
should be here or you can just go to
PostgreSQL and here you have pgAdmin
as well and here is the application Stack
Builder. Alright, but if you want to work
with Python you want to access the
PostgreSQL databases through Python so
you don't have to interact with these
applications here. The way to interact
with PostgreSQL with Python is by
installing psycopg2 and you can
install psycopg2 with pip.
However you may run into problems
because psycopg2 is written in C so
you need C compiler installed in your
system on Windows at least. You will not
have this problem on a Mac and Linux.
I am quite sure. The solution to this?
Actually there are a few solutions.
One of the solutions is that you may want
to install visual studio on your Windows
machine, but that's quite a big programs
and I wouldn't want to install that, so the
second solution which I prefer the most
is to use precompiled Python libraries.
And you can find almost any Python
libraries that require C compiler you
can find those libraries in this page
served by Christoph Goblke, so we're
looking for psycopg2. Here you
have the whl files, so a whl file is a
file that can be installed with pip so
what you do when you install something
with pip, pip install psycopg2, pip is
downloading the whl file from the
remote server and then it installs it in
your system, so here you can look for
your version and this would be the file
for my system.
So I'll just get this from here and paste it
in here so that I can access it from the
Atom command line, so here is the file
that I just downloaded so just go ahead
and pip install and then you will need
to point to the whl file,
so dot whl, alright.
And that was successfully installed. I can
quickly check if that is available and
it seems to be working. You can also
check the version of your library if you
want, so it's 2.6.1.
Alright so in the next lecture we will
connect to the database to the postgreSQL
database and then we'll be creating
tables and inserting data, viewing
deleting and updating them.
So let's move on.