Very good, in this lecture you will learn, how
to connect to a PostgreSQL database, how
to create tables in a PostgreSQL
database, insert data, view data and
delete and update rows as well.
The script you're looking at now
though is the script that you build in
the previous lectures using a SQLite
database, so if you haven't watched those
lectures are highly recommended to go
through them first, then you come here
because in this lecture I'll just go
through this code and replace only a few
lines of them and that suggests that the
code that you use for sqlite3 library
is very similar to the code we'll use
for a psycopg2 which is a library
used to connect to PostgreSQL databases.
The main difference is that your
database will not be a DB file storing
your file system.
It will be a database embedded in your
PostgreSQL installation, and so the first
requirement is that you need to have an
existing database in your PostgreSQL
database server, and PostgreSQL comes
with a default database, so once you
install PostgreSQL you'll have.
a database called Postgres so we can just
pass the database here. Or if you like
you can create your own database, so you
just need to go to your PostgreSQL
installation and you can create a
database through pgAdmin, so here are
your database servers and this is a
default one. You need to connect to your
database server first. Then this would be
the password that you created when you
install Postgres. Postgres123 was mine.
All right so I was successfully
connected and I have three databases.
So this is the default database that I was
talking about and these are two other
databases I have created. So to create a
a new database just right click on
databases and then new database. Let's say
database1 and you need to specify the
owner, so the user of your database.
Postgres, this is what I specified
when I installed PostgreSQL and this should
a database here. If you click to that you
will connect to it. Now you can just call
this and go back to Python.
Ok let me first comment these lines out
so when I execute the script
I don't get this function instances called.
So we have an empty database so the
first thing we would like to do is to
create a table, but first of all I would
like to change this to psyco2 and
of course I would like to make a
batch placement of SQLite3.
Replace it with psycopg2, so I want
all these library names here to be
placed with a psycopg2, so replace all
and just press escape and that goes away.
Luckily this code is the same as
sqlite3 library so we have connects
and then we have a cursor object, then we
have the execute method, commit, and close.
All we have to do is change the
parameters here, and here we would want
to pass the database name, the user name,
the host, the password and the port
number of your database server, and all
that comes inside quotes.
So it is passed as a string to the
connect method. First we have
the database name, so the parameter dbname
and that will be equal to a value, so you
need to insert the value inside single
quotes, so that is database 1, the name of
the database. Then you have user and be
aware that you don't need to use commas
in here so all this goes as a string and
it is read as a string by the connect
method, so user goes inside quotes.
Postgres then we have the password
Posgres123, then you have
the hostname, so the host parameter
and that should be localhost.
Alright so local host should be your host
name and it's always like that.
and last we have the port number and
that goes inside quotes as well so 5432.
So those are the parameters you pass to
your connection method of the psycopg2
library. Then let's try to call that
function, so create table is the function
and I'll save the script so let me make
sure you know what it's happening here.
So we connect to the database and then we
have the same methods for the psycopg2
library so we are creating a table
name store and then we have three
columns for that table, and we commit
those changes and we close the connection
so save the script, CTRL S and then
call the script and that looks
successful. If you like you can just go
to pgAdmin and here you can see the
table that you have just created, so just
enter the password and you need to go to
your database, so database1 expand that.
Then you need to go to schemas
public, tables and this is our table name.
So we have the store table and you
got three columns, item, quantity and price.
All right, we have an empty table
so let's go ahead and insert some data
to that table.
I'll just copy this connection string
and paste it in here. Then remember that
we use question marks when inserting
values for sqlite3.
If you want you could use
string formatting placeholders.
So one for the item, the one for
quantity and another one for the price.
and then after coma, let me delete this.
After the quotes sorry, you'd pass
the percentage, so you're ready now string
formatting and then you specify the
tuple of the variables you want to
insert here, so item, quantity, and price.
So you can use this but this would be
prone to SQL injections from attackers,
so it's not a good idea. I can ahead and
execute this actually just to see what
happens so let's say Apple, and 10, and 15
for the price. Let me execute this, so it
looks like it worked and we can check it
in the table here. So you can just go to
your database which is database1 and
here you can execute a simple SQL query.
Select all from store and go to run and
you see that Apple was added to the table,
so it works, but it's risky to use
Python string formatting so what you
want to do is, I'll just leave it for
a while there so that you compare
things out, and to avoid SQL injections you
should actually pass your variables as a
second parameter to the execute method.
So what does that mean is you don't have
to use quotes, so you just pass
%s just like that, and then you
put a comma here so that that means this
string inside double quotes is
the 1 argument and then
this one here is the other argument and then
you pass your variables so that should
work now. So I'm sure you can see the
difference between this and this.
And I'll just comment this out so that it
isn't executed and let's say orange same
price and quantity. Execute and let's get
and check in pgAdmin, so let me execute
the query again and you see that orange was
added as a new row to the table. So this
is the way to go and I'll delete this.
Alright, now let's look at the view
function, so what a few function is doing
is it connects to the database and it
selects all the rows from the store
table, and then we store those rows in the
row variable using the fetch all method
and then we return those rows as a function
output. Everything you need to change
here is the argument of the connect
method, so just put them here and you
should be good to go.
So let me view, call the function, and execute.
And yeah, we need to print it. Forgot it.
And yeah, so we got Apple, and we got three
oranges now because when I executed
the script here I got the insert
function executed again so we got two
oranges and another one when you used
string formatting placeholders, so you
get the idea. Let's look at the delete
function. Again we need to pass the arguments
of psycopg2 connection. Then we
have delete from store where item again
we can't use a question mark so we need
to use %s, and then as a second
argument we pass the item variable,
so it is same as sqlite3, but we use
%s here and let me call delete.
I'll comment this out and delete here so what
you want to delete is the item. What item?
Let's say we want to delete rows
where the item is equal to orange, also
let's see how this goes. And yeah,
the item was deleted. The rows with the item
orange were deleted and we got the view
function executed, so we got one row now.
Our table has only one row. A quick look at
the update method now. Just like that.
And here we are updating the store table,
and there we are setting, so we are updating
the quantity to this value and the price
as well to this value where the item is equal
to this value. All right so we got
1, 2, 3 values and we pass three
variables here after the coma, so as a
second argument of the execute method,
and the update method gets three arguments.
Let me comment this out and update.
We have only morrow so I would like to
set the quantity of apples to
let's say 20 and the price let's give
the price the same and for the item
Apple, just like that, and execute.
And we got the quantity changed to 20,
so that was it.
I believe that was quite simple so if you
learned sqlite3 before, this was
quite simple for you, and if you have any
question just feel free to drop them in
the discussion section. I'll be happy to
answer. See in the next lecture.