Hi there and welcome
to the Python Mega Course:
Build 10 Real World Applications.
I assume you're curious to know what
this course contains, and you also want
to know what you will achieve by
completing this course, so that's what
this introductory video is all about.
My name is Ardit Sulce and I have been
teaching on Udemy more than one and a half years
now and I have thousands of students
and thousands reviews on my courses as well.
I'm also a freelancer mainly using Python
for data analysis and visualization.
I have worked in the GIS sector as well
where Python has a very respected
position. Back to the course content now.
You don't need any previous knowledge of
Python to take this course. The course
will take you from zero and you'll build
up the skills slowly and advance them as
you will build these 10 applications.
This is called a Mega Course because
first, it has 22 hours of content and
second, the course will guide you on how
to create 10 large applications in
different areas of Python starting from
data analysis to visualizations on the
web and web apps with data bases and
many more, and specifically you will
build these 10 applications. First, you
start small by first building a program
that generates texts given
some user-defined rules.
Then, as the second application
you'll build a program that creates
Web Maps, and after that you'll build
a program that blocks access to certain
websites in certain hours during the day
in your computer. This program has been
quite useful for me personally as it
doesn't let me browse destructive
websites while I'm working,
so that improves my productivity.
And then as the fourth application you are
going to build a website with Python and
the Flask framework and not just that,
but you will also learn how to deploy
the website in a live server so that
everyone can see your website through
the website URL address. Then you will build
a desktop program that interacts with
a database and lets users store, delete,
and view data through the program graphical
user interface which you are going to build
with Python. Next you will create a program
that starts the computer webcam and
start recording a video, and in detects
movement live in the video frame that
is being captured, and so the program
also records motion data and produces a
web graph with an overview of the motion
that took place in front of the camera.
And all this process is fully automatic.
Next you will create a web scraper which
is a program that extracts data from
websites and stores those data in a web
structure format such as CSV or Excel files.
Then you'll create a web app which
visualizes stock market data on a web page.
This is very useful for people who work
on data analysis and visualizations.
After that you'll build a web app using
Python and the flask web framework. This
web app will have a PostgreSQL database
as well in the backend, and in the frontend
it will have an HTML form where users
can submit data and then the program
sends an automatic email to the users
with some statistics extracted from the
back-end database. So that's a very
interesting web application with lots of
features, and lastly you will create a
web application that lets users submit
addresses of locations, and the program
converts those addresses to geographic
numeric coordinates and lets the user
download the output through the web page.
So that's about the 10 applications.
All the content is yours and you have
unlimited access, however here is my
advice now. Let's be honest,
if all you do is watching the videos
without trying the code
that I show in the videos, you won't be
able to learn Python easily. You cannot
learn how to drive a car by just
watching someone else do it, right?
So make sure you write and play around with
the code I show you the videos
and don't just copy my code, but try to
experiment, change some parts of the code,
Run the program again and see how the
output changes. Also try to solve the
assignments you are given because there
are a few assignments throughout the course.
And also ask questions in the Q&A area,
so in the question-and-answer area.
Do internet research and be persistent
on solving code issues which always
arise while programming no matter how
good you are. If you do all that you'll
have very good control of the Python
programming language and you'll be ready
to apply for at least an entry-level job
after you finish this course. That's about
the course. Now feel free to go to the
next lecture and I wish you good luck!
Thanks!