Great, before we go ahead and learn about
the Python basic such as variables,
functions and so on I think it's good
that's you understand how a Python
program looks like. This is especially
good if you have never programed before.
languages you may have three kinds of
programs and I'll tell you why we have
three kinds of programs so you may have
a program with a command line interface
such as this one here. You may have a
program with a graphical user interface
such as this one here, so it's a desktop
application and you may also have for
web applications such as this one in
here that runs on the browser and it
can be accessed through the internet.
Now the first thing you should know is that
all these programs they are based on a
dot py file such as this ones in here
so this is a Python file and whenever
you start building something you should
write your code in this script I which
looks like this one here, anyway and then
once you have that script you can either
run it through the command line interface
such as this one, script 4.py
Execute it and then you communicate with
the interface so your program your
Python program is asking you to enter
some letters in there and so enter V V
and c for consonants consonants. L or C, anyway
and get some output in the command line
Interface. Now when do you use such a program?
Well, you do this program if you not
planning to distribute this program to
normal users, to people who don't know
programming so I use Python,
the Python program which I have
already installed and I show and I'll
show you how to install that later so I
use Python and that points to the Python
script so to the Python program to execute
the program. Now, normal users they don't have
Python installed or they don't know how
to execute a Python program and that's
why you have
graphical user interface there such as
this one, or browsers such as this one
in here and yeah why don't you use
desktop application such as this? Well you'd
use that if you just want to distribute
your program to a specific number of
users let's say you work on a
company and you will want to build a
program for the employees of a company
to do specific tasks and so you could
build this program and it's possible to
create an executable file out of your
Python program. This particular one is
A dot exe file for Windows, it runs on
Windows as a standalone program but you
can also create dot app files for Mac
computers and then the user they don't
need to have for installed. They would
simply execute the dot exe file and they
can use the application so yeah, that's
the application. We will be building all these
three applications in the course so the
command line interface, the web
application and the desktop based
application and then you have
web applications such as this one you here.
So when would you use a web application?
Well the web applications are best when
your audience is large so basically you
may want as many users to your
application as possible so for
instance what we have here is this is a
geocoder service. It geocodes, it converts
addresses to latitude and longitude
coordinates so what users can do here is
they can choose a file, so s CSV file and
then you calculate latitude and
longitude and send them back as csv file
with those values so a web application in
simple words can be for anyone and this
also is based on dot py files on the
background so I will show these files
for now we're going to build all these
applications as I told you so,
yeah that's about this lecture I hope you
have a clear idea now
Of what a program, a Python program looks
like and what you can do with Python as well.
If you have questions please feel
free to ask them in the Q&A section, so in
the discussion area of the course and
yeah I'll be happy to help you. Hope you
enjoyed this and I'll to talk you in the next
lectures.