Hello there and welcome to this new
lecture! In this lecture I'll show you
how to set up Python in your computer.
Specifically these instructions are for
Windows users so if you are a Mac or
Linux user you can skip this lecture
and you can go to the next lecture where
I'll show you how to set up Python on a
Mac and instructions also work for Linux
users so Windows users please follow if
you haven't installed Python yet, we're
going to download and install python and
also try Python out. And so you go to
python.org that's the official Python
website and you go to downloads and here
you'll see the latest Python version.
Currently it is 3.6.0.
Just click that and save file.
Also notice that there's also a version
of Python 2 so Python 2.7 to be exact
but Python 2 is not being supported
anymore after 2020 so Python 2 is slowly
retiring so it's advisable to use Python
3 this one in here and once you have
downloaded the dot exe file just click it.
Run. You can choose to install it in the
default directory but you can also do a
customized installation if you want to
change the directory, anyway make sure
you have checked this option at Python
3.6 to PATH so I'm going to go with the
default installation process. Yeah that
was it. Set up was successful. You can
close the window now and we can go ahead
and open Pythom so how do we do that
on windows? Well we can press the
Windows key button, so we're talking
about the Win key. By pressing it you
will be able to search on the start
button, alternatively you can simply go
to the start button, click it and then
type cmd and then click on c armed.exe
and that will open the windows command prompt.
And so this is like the terminal
on Mac or Linux. On Mac and Linux it
is referred to as the terminal on
Windows it is referred to as a comand
prompt or command line. To open Python all
you have to do is type in Python and
that will open an interactive session of
Python and an interactive session is
best for testing out so here you can
write lines of code one by one like that
and you promptly get the results in here.
So this is why we call it interactive, but
you cannot, it's not very appropriate to
write multiple lines of code, so let's
say you have a program that has 10 lines
of code and in that case you'd want to
write those lines in a file, in a Python
file but we will cover that later and
this is the interactive shell this is
good for testing, so before you do a
program you are not sure about certain
aspects, certain commands that you
want to include, certain keywords that
you want including in your program so you
test things out in here very quickly.
This is very efficient and it's also
good for learning. To exit the
interactive shell you press exit and
brackets, open and closing brackets.
Now something you maybe, you probably noted
was that the Python that I opened was version
3.5.2 but why is that because I
installed Python 3.6 in here, 3.6, so why did
I get five Python 3.5.2?
Well the answer is that I already had
Python 3.5.2
installed on my Windows so in other words
before I install Python 3.6 I could
trigger a Python shell like that so the
question is how do I run Python 3.6 now?
Well the first thing you should know is
that there is no problem having multiple
Python installations in your system, the
key here is that you have to assign
different commands to each of your
Python
instalations so for instance Python 3.5.2
has these commands
to run Python. Now for Python 3.6
we need to assign another
command and I'll go and search for the
installation directory of
Python 3.6 so open that and now Windows
when you search for Python, when you
enter the Python command here, Windows is
looking at the path variable, the Windows
path variable and it's searching for
this type of command Python but this
was already occupied by another so by
Python 3.5.2, that's why it
triggers Python 3.5.2,
so in that case you may want to do
trick here, let's say do Python 36 and
restart that command prompt and then
run again python 36 and you get Python 36.
So that's the trick and again of course
you can do operations here and so on
Of course you still have Python 3.5 at
least I have Python 3.5 maybe you don't
because you didn't have any Python
installed just yet, so that's the idea.
On your system if you install Python for
the first time, if you install
Python 3.6 you'll be
able to execute Python with this commands.
Python. If you had an existing Python
installation and you install a new one,
no problem, you can run Python 36 like I did
I hope this was clear and I hope you are
up and running now with Python
And I'll talk to you in the next lectures.