Hey hello again in this lecture I'll
show you how to download and install the
Atom editor. Atom is a powerful and
very efficient editor for writing and
executing Python code. This lecture is
specifically for windows, so for Mac
users please go to the next lecture.
So before what we did was we installed
Python and we tried a python interactive
session in the command prompt and we
also created a python program using a
simple editor such as Notepad or
whatever editor you had in on your
Windows, so now we're going to use
another editor which is Atom and you
need to go and install it from and
download it from the Atom official web
Page, just click the button there.
Say file and it will take a while until it
downloads. Great, the download process
has finished now so I'm going to click
on Atom, click on run to run
the installation and yeah you have to wait a
while until Atom is installed.
And yeah, the installation was quick and now Atom has
been opened on my Windows, however I would
like to close it here and show you the
standard way of how to open Atom, so the
way that you'd normally open Atom
when you start programming so one way to
open Atom is to browse through your
programs and open Atom by clicking.
However that we open atom in a random
directory so the most efficient way to
open Atom is to go to the directory
where you have your programs so the
program that we have is myprogram.py.
And then outside in here right click
and go to open with Atom, but if you
don't see open with Atom like I do. so
I don't have open with Atom for now,
then go and open Atom
for your programs. Go to file, settings
and then check these two options so this
options were under system, under the
system tab of the settings menu and I
close Atom and I right click and now
you should see this menu in here. Open it
and you should now see this view but if
you see, if you don't see the tree
view in here, the directory tree view, go to
view and then toggle tree view so you can
toggle it off and on. You can close this
and then to open your program, so to edit
your program you simply double-click
your file your Python file and yeah, you
start writing. Print. Start adding more
code and always press ctrl s to save and
now to execute this code you can either
go here and open your command window
here with Shift right click or there is a
more efficient way to do it. You need
to go to file settings, packages, sorry
install, you want to install a new
package and search for that platformio
click install and so this is the package
that we will install or will integrate a
terminal, a command line inside Atom so
you don't have to use external windows
and native windows command line and you
can run your programs from within Atom.
All right, platform ide terminal was
installed successfully, you can close the
settings tab and so now you should see
this plus icon in here, click on the icon.
Will open a new terminal so now this is
opening the current directory which
reflects the directory of your Atom
directory, so of your programs. Now you
can go ahead and type in commands you to
run your Python program, so my tab for
auto completion and that will
auto complete like that, don't worry about this.
This just means the current
directory, so when you do Tab, Tab will
add this. Ignore it and press Enter and
you see the program output in the
terminal. You can clear the terminal from
the codes from previously executed
commands and of course you can call
previously executed commands with the
upper arrow key. Execute again and don't
confuse executing a program with opening
a Python interactive session, so here you
write Python code like print 7 for
example interactively but if you exit
this because I see some students will go
ahead and run Python code in here but
this is wrong, this is not Python,
this is windows, the windows command line, so
don't do that instead write Python code
inside an interactive session or inside
the Python file. That's the idea and
this is Atom. I hope you like it
and I'll talk to you later.