Hello there and welcome to this new
section of the course. In the previous
section so through all the lectures of
the previous section I covered how to
set up Python on your computer and also
the Atom editor and also show you how to
create a Python program which is this
one in here that we created, so at this
point you should have an editor and you
should know how to create a Python file
and write some code in it like this one
in here. Now in this new section what
I'll cover is variables and data types.
So in the next lecture you'll be able to
create and understand variables and in
the lectures after that you're going to
learn about the various data types that
we use in Python so in this video I just
wanted to introduce you to this new
section and let's go to the next video
where I'll explain variables see you.