Hi again, in this lecture I'll show you
how to do math operations with numbers.
So we're going to look at math operators.
Let's go straight away and open a Python
section and let me write a math
expression there. 20 minus 10 divided by
5 times 3 in the power of 2 and what we
get is 2.0. So why did I write this a
long expression? Well because I want to
explain to you the order of operators so
when you have multiple operators in an
expression the one to be executed
first is the exponent, so we have 3 in
power of 2 here that will give us 9.
So power is the first to be executed and
also that is division and multiplication.
Actually division and
multiplication are on the same level.
We're talking about order but the one
that is first will be executed first so in
this case division is the first one so
what will happen here is Python will
ignore minus for now,
so it will divide 10 by 5 and it will
give 2 then it will do 2 times 9.
So again 10 divided by 5, 2 times 9, 19.
And then we have the rest of the operators
which could be a plus or minus so in
this case we have minus so 20 minus 18.
We have 2.0. You'd ask why we have 2.0?
Because 10 divided by 5 gives 2.0.
So division outputs a float in Python 3.
If you are on Python 2, it would output
an integer. Now to make your expressions
look better, you'd want to remove the
spaces for the power operator and also
you do like that somehow you can read it
better,
so 2 times 9 and then 20 minus 18 and so on.
You get the idea.
You get 2.0 again and now if you want to
execute the minus operator first
you'd want to put that inside brackets.
So why did we get 18? Well because 20
minus 10 gives 10 and then 10 divided by
5 gives 2 and then 2 times 9 gives 18.
That's the idea. And then you could also do
this, put these in brackets and what
would happen here is you know 10 here,
15 here in the power of 2, so 15 in the
power of 2, and then 10, so 10 divided by
15 in the power of 2. Let's see what we get.
Yeah we got that, so let's see if I was
Right.
15 in the power of 2 we get 225.
And then we got 10 on the other side, so 10
divided by 225. We get that number.
So whenever you want to change the
order of operators, you should use
brackets and so I hope you get the idea
and please try this out, so try to do a
few operations with numbers to get used to it.
And yeah, I'll talk to you later.
Thanks.