Great, now let's look at lists, so in the
previous lecture we were looking at
strings and indexing and splitting
strings and I will be working with lists
which are very similar to strings. They
are similar because they are both
referred to as sequences, so there are
sequences of items. The difference is
that, let me open Python, and so the
difference is that the string is made of
other strings so it can contain only
strings of characters or strings.
whatever you like to call it, however
lists can contain various other data
types, let's say H a letter, a number, and
also a string. So this is a string the
first one, this is a number, an integer.
This is also string with multiple
characters and that is a list, so for
this you want to use square brackets to
create a list. Execute and yeah you can
call it and so this is a list of three
items and you can also store other
objects in a list but we'll cover other
objects in later sections, you know we
have table of objects with lots of data.
You may store files in a list you may
store widgets of a graphical user
interface that you are building and so
on, so these are very useful and lists also
have indexing and you can split lists,
you can extract items and so on. So the
good news is that lists have the
same indexing system as strings and so
you've learned that in the previous
lecture and you can go ahead and apply
that system not, so let's extract number 2.
That would have an index of one.
Execute that and yeah you get 2 there. If you
check the type you'll see that's an integer.
So every item of a list has its own
data type, even also access more than
white one item of a list. Let's say
you want the first two items. You do 0 1 2, so
like that or 0 to 2 whatever you like.
That will produce another list so the
type of this split is a list. The type of
the split of a string is a string, so S
for the string here, C for the list.
Lists now have methods associated with
them just like strings do and so you can
check what methods you have available
there by just doing a dir list.
So this a the blueprint you can use
lists, you can pass empty square brackets
in there, it's the same thing and then
you can use help to look at each of
these methods, so these are the methods.
Without the underscore and let's look at
the append method, so to apply methode
you do c the dot notation append and here
on that 3. What that does, it adds
another item to the end of the list,
So it appends an item to the
list and you can explore the other
methods if you like so let's say help.
Remove like that and you'll see how to
use that remove method, so you do
c.remove and then you pass the value of
the item that you want to remove, so
not the index but the value. Let's say we
want to remove 2 and you see that 2
is now gone from the list so look
at the other methods of the list and try
to experiment with this and play around
with them access items and split them
and you'll be good to go then.
Thanks, I'll talk to you later.