Let's now look at tuples. In the
previous lecture we looked at lists and
tuples are very similar to lists, the
only difference is that tuples are not
mutable, so you cannot change a tuple.
Lists are used much more than tuples
so tuples are only using very specific
scenarios, so we will see some scenarios
throughout the course when we build the
real-world applications, so you don't
have to worry about understanding when
to use a tuple in programming for now.
Anyway I want to show you the syntax, so
you can create a tuple like that.
So tuples just like lists, they contain
they may contain different data types.
Let's say 3 4 and so on.
Oh sorry, I was writing in the
terminal, let me open the Python shell so
again
we have strings numbers and floats if you like.
Whatever type that you want you can pass
in a tuple and in a list and of course
you can use indexing for tuples as well,
so let's access the lost item and that
will give 4.6. The difference is that you
know tuples they have some slight
different methods than lists, so if you
dir list, you see that lists have
much more methods available than tuples,
so for instance you can append items to
a list, you can clear the list and copy
and count, count is available for tuples
because count doesn't change the data type,
so it doesn't change the tuple, it just
counts how many items are there in the tuple.
As I said, tuples are immutable, so you
cannot change them that's why these
methods that change the data type like
inserting new values and popping out
values, removing
values, reversing and sorting so these
are not available and yeah this is more or
less about tuples. In case you need them
later they are there for you. Hope you're
enjoying the course and I'll talk to you later.