Hi and welcome to this new section! In
this section you're going to learn about
two very important concepts in
programming. These are functions and
conditionals. Functions, functions are
used to keep your code more organized so
think of functions as small chunks of
code which together build a program that
is what you need to know for now.
Functions are useful for other things as
well but you'll understand it as you
build the real world programs. In the next
video I'll write a function but that is
just a standalone function, so it
doesn't interact with other parts of the
code, it's just a function, but when you
see the large applications later on
you'll see how the function integrates
with other parts of the code, so that's a
good thing of creating reload programs.
That is how you'll learn how to do
programming in real life. That's about
functions and then in this section you'll
also learn conditionals which basically
are used to have your program make
decisions, so if that number is greater
than that do this, if it's not greater
than do this other thing, that's
basically the idea, but you'll see it in
action, so this is about the introduction
of this section. I'll see you in the
other lecture.