Hi, here is one more lecture about functions
and this one is in a more practical view
because what we're going to do is we're
going to, save that, we're going to look at
the program that we built in the previous
lecture, sorry in the previous section so
this simple program. Know that these are
the real-life applications that this
course covers, so these are just a small
snippet of code, don't confuse this
with the real-life applications. I will
cover 10 real world applications later in
course. Until in this program will this
did was it asked you for the age and
let me guess M that's not exactly my age
but anyway 90, so this will print out
your age plus 50, so 90 in this
case and what I want to do in this
lecture is I want to organize this code
better by putting this inside a function
so this will help you understand
functions, how they are used in a more
real-life situation. So the function
basically had three components and that
was input, the body of the functions,
so the operations that the function
performs, and then the output so in this
case we are going to somehow get the
input from this, user prompt and then
this will be a body of our function and
then we will output this one here.
The new age variable so let's go ahead and
define a function here, define age foo.
Let's keep it like that and we're going to
get some age input there and there
goes this line, so the new age will be
equal to the input that the function
will pass in here.
So we convert that input to float and
then we add 50 to that and then we return
new age, so once you have defined a
blueprint so to say,
once you define your function, then you
want to prompt the user for a value, so
that you have a value already there to
pass it to the function code later here.
Which will be like print age foo age
goes there. Now don't confuse this age
variable with this one here, they just
happen to be the same but these are not
the same because this is a local
variable,
while this one in here is a local, global
variable, sorry. Global variable, local
variable so what happens is when Python
executes this script it goes line by
line, so it reads the first line, second,
third and it knows, it sort of records
in the memory this kind of blueprint
but anyway this is just a blueprint so
it will not output anything, and then it goes
to the next line this is empty, okay go
to the next line. Age equals to input.
We have an input function which creates a
user prompt, so it prompts the user this
message and then the user
submits a value and that value is
stored in the age variable.
So this is a global variable. It doesn't have to do
with this one here and then what happens
is we call the function age foo and inside
that function we pass the value stored in
this age global variable, so let's say the
user passed 40. 40 will be passed in
here so 40 here which means this 40
will be passed to this age argument
so to this variable, so the local
variable now we'll get a value of 40 and
that value will be put in here, so float
40 plus 50 equals 90 and that will
return 90, so that 90 will replace this
thing in here and Python will print 90
point zero in the command prompt in the
terminal here. Let me try that. Enter age.
40. 90 point zero. And yes
basically that's how you integrate user
inputs with functions. That's about this
lecture. I'll talk to you later.