Hey, hello again. In this lecture you're going to learn
about conditionals. What is a conditional?
Well a conditional is a block of code which
performs different actions depending on
whether a given conditional evaluates to
true or false so let's go ahead and
create a conditional in Python. I'll create the
file conditionals dot py and let me
create a conditional block, and first of
all let me create a variable. Let's say a
equals five and here I'll create a
conditional block. This block, what this
will do is it will perform an action if
a is less than five and another action
if a is equal or greater than five
so let me create that. If this, our
conditional starts if a and let's say
less than five print, let's say less than 5.
Press ENTER and if you want to perform
more actions with this conditional, with
this condition so when this condition is
true this will be executed but if you
want to perform more actions you can add
one there, if not then you can go to the
next check.
So that would be else, so you have a
column here, a column there, so else print
equal or greater than 5. Now let me
execute it. And we get equal or greater
than 5. So why did you get that? Well
because you know if a is less than 5
which is not, so this evaluates to false,
that means with this this will not be
executed so Python will skip this line
and it will go to the next one. This next
line says else, so else means if this
is not true,
this will be executed, so equal or
greater than five, so in this case if a
is not less than five then there's no
other option but a is either equal or
greater than five, so that's an if and else
conditional block. However if you want to
add more conditions there
you want to use elif, so let's do that
the first two lines stay the same. If a
is less than five print less than five
elif a is equal to five print equal to
five else print greater than five. Save
and execute and you get equal to five.
If a was six,
you'd get greater than five and if a was
three you'd get less than five.
That's a conditional block in Python and
yeah, try to get familiar with the syntax
and in the next lecture I'm going to
incorporate a conditional with this
block of code, so see you there.