Hi and welcome to this new section where
you'll learn about object-oriented
programming often referred to as OOP
for short. Now if you have experience
with programming that's probably a
familiar concept for you because OOP
is used in most of the languages,
but I assume you don't know anything
about object-oriented programming so
I'll explain the concept from the
beginning. Now there are various
definitions of OOP out there and some
get very tricky, but I believe the best
one to know is that object-oriented
programming is just a way to organize
your code. That means Opie is not a must.
So you can simply use functions to build
an application as we did here with our
bookstore application, and many
programmers choose to not use
object-oriented programming to organize
their code, they don't use the OOP way
to write their code in other words.
However it is generally accepted that if
you have more than two functions which
apply operations to the same object,
for instance a program that applies
operations to a tkinter interface, so
you have this callback functions, and so
you should organize these functions into
something called a class. Now because
object-oriented programming is a complex
concept I didn't include that in the
beginning of this course, so I wanted
that you first built some applications
using functions which is more intuitive,
and then you move to object-oriented
programming. So back to our graphical
user interface application. So the object
here, I'm talking about objects and the object
here is the entire window with buttons
and other widgets as well now we can put
all the attributes that define this
object so this window such as
the title of the buttons, the label,
and also the callback functions
attached to this object inside the class.
So in our application we didn't use
classes, we used functions so this script
here does not apply to object-oriented
programming, and putting this object
inside a class means we are organizing
the code in a class which creates,
an object so that's why we call it
object-oriented programming.
And using classes to organize your code
is referred to as object-oriented
programming, and what I'll do next is in
my backend script where I have the database
operations I'll transform this script by
putting this inside a class and after
that you can do the same for the frontend
interface so that you practice
object-oriented programming. Now my
purpose here is not to train you how to
write classes. I first want you to
understand classes, and many learning
resources explain object-oriented
programming by saying something like we
create a class that creates a dog object,
and the dogs can eat, and bark and so on.
That's a good example to train
you to learn the syntax of a class, but
hey what is a dog in in programming?
I mean you can scratch your head
all day trying to come up with
a scenario where you have a dog as an
object in your application, and then that
still a good example, but only if you have
some years of experience in programming,
and you can quickly think of where and
when to use classes based on such
examples. I assume you don't have these
years of experience, so I'll use
real programming objects in this section
to explain such a tricky concept as
object-oriented programming. So the best
way to understand OOP is to first build
a program with a known object oriented
programming approach, so using functions,
and once you know that program well, then
you build that program again using
OOP, and then you automatically
understand what OOP is by looking at how
things are different. So let me organize
this code using classes now and later
we will build a simpler program from
scratch where we create a bank
account object with Python, and we will
apply functions to that object such as
withdraw, deposit, and so on. That's great,
and yeah, that's about this
introduction, and let's move on to the
next lecture and write some classes.