Good, now I'll go ahead and transform
this script into an object oriented
programming style, so in other words I'll
organize these functions in a more
efficient way and just to refresh your
memory what this script does, so we have
a back-end and front-end script, and the
front-end what it does is it constructs
the graphical user interface so
you know that. And we have this books dot
db database file, and there are some data
there and you can search for entries so
for rows in the database, add new and so on.
And this frontend.py constructs
the graphical user interface
and this backend is responsible for the
database interaction, and so
object-oriented programming is about
encapsulating functions inside a class.
So class, and let's call this database.
Yeah, that's it basically we still have a
lot of things to do but, let's think
thing about what is this database class.
Well, whenever you decide to use
object-oriented programming you first
need to think about the object that you
want to use which is the object that
that you want to apply this methods to
and in our case that would be the
database, so then we insert data to the
tables of this database and view data
and so on.
Now this object, this object you first
need to create a minimal object when you
call the class, and I'll show you how you
call a class in a minute, but for now
let's focus on creating the blueprint
of the object. So you create the
blueprint of the object which is this one
here, and then you create object
instances using that blueprint, and you
do that by calling the class. Now when
you call the class you want to have
this minimal object, so in this case that
would be to establish a connection to
this database, and then create a coursor
object, and maybe check for tables so
that you make sure that your database
has a table, and so that it allows you to
do later apply methods to this table of
database, otherwise the database
would be useless, so it needs to have
a table and an established connection.
That means you have to figure out a way
that when you call the class these lines
here are executed. And Python has
reserved a special syntax for that.
So the first function of your script you
need to call it init with double
underscore in front and on the back.
So that's an init function which means
initialize an object. In other
programming languages that is called
a constructor so, it constructs the object.
So when you call a class, this function
is executed but not the other ones.
The other ones are executed if you refer
to them like in this case that would be
something like a database dot insert,
and then you pass the parameters, the
arguments there. Now we have quite a few
things to add here in script for this to
work, but I'd prefer to do this on a trial
and error base, so we'll execute it, we'll
see whatever we get so that you understand
how things are working there, so what
I'll do I'll call this class as it is
now, so we don't need this function. This
function is gone now because I replaced that
with init, so you know you don't call
functions anymore like we did here, so
for instance here we are calling
functions from the backend module so
which is like a module, you are importing
this as a module. And in this case now
what we do is from the backend import
database, so we import the database class
from the backend script so that makes
available the database class for us so
the database blueprint. So this is just
a blueprint. Now we need to create an
object out of this blueprint, so let's
call that object database and that
would be equal to database, so the class
and so let's, for now let's not pass any
arguments there, and then we need to replace
these references, so we don't do back-end
anymore, we do database dot view. So we
are referring to the view function of
the database object which is an instance
of this class.
Great, so we go ahead and replace
these other ones with database, so
back-end replace that, replac, replace.
Yeah, that's it. This is the script name.
And it should be like that. Escape here.
Great, now I'll go ahead and execute that,
so don't expect this to work but we have
to look closely to the error trying to
understand what it says. So trace back
file frontend dot py line 4, here so in it takes 0
positional argument,  but one was given.
And what's happening here now is that
when you call the class this, class will
create an object instance, and store it
in this variable, and then it sends this
object instance to this function.
So let me split this on the right so that we
have both the scripts in here, so the frontend
and the backend, so basically
this database object instance is
being sent to this init object even
though this is an empty bracket.
So that's like a hidden syntax there and
to fix this you need to perform a trick
here, so it says init takes zero
positional arguments because it actually
it has an empty bracket here, so it's
like a normal function, and functions if
you don't put a parameter there, but then
you pass a parameter when you call it,
the function will say I don't take any
positional arguments or any mandatory
arguments but one argument was given to
me so I'll throw an error. Now to fix that
you need to pass a parameter there and
everyone passes self there, so you can
pass any word, that that is still work,
but as a convention so that so that your
code is readable by other people you
need to pass self. So now your init
function takes in a parameter and when
you call this class, this class will send
object instance, and that object instance
will go inside this parameter. So this
parameter will be replaced by the object
instance argument. Great, if you still
don't understand that, I'm sure you'll do
so later as you write more classes. Good.
Now I'll go ahead and save this and this,
and try out the script again, and great.
So that means that the class was
successfully initialized, and it created
on the object basis for us. Let me
close this, and maybe add something there.
This is not necessary, but just to
show you that if you want to add more
parameters to your init function you do
something like db, and then replace this
with db, and then here you pass the
argument that will be passed to this db
parameter, so that would be books
dot db, the file path to our database.
Great, and if you agree do this again
you get the same result.
So what's happening here is that Python
is first sending the database object
instance to the self parameter and then
it sends the path of the file to
the db parameter, and that db parameter
sends that file path to the db parameter
over the connect method. Great, now let's
see how these methods will work, so we
have the view all button which if we
press it what will happen is the view
function of the database class, actually
the view method of the database class
will be executed, so this one here. Let's
see if we were able to get it. Well an error.
Let me close this. So it says view takes
zero positional arguments, but one was
given, so that again suggests that when
you call a method of class, the class is
sending the object instance to that
method as well just as we did with the
init function. That means we need to do
the trick again.
So just pass self there, and you try out
again, see whatever we get this time.
Well, no error things are working obviously.
So that's great, however if you try the other
methods now like insert, you'll probably get
an error, so let me try that. So View all
is working fine, but if we insert
something let's say "Hey There" and…
And yeah, add entry. So insert takes four
positional arguments, but five were given.
So insert and these values are being
passed to these parameters, but also we
are passing the object instance, so let's
go ahead and add self there, and I'll do the
same for search as well, delete and update.
And yeah, that's what we have. Looks good.
Let's try out again, so view all and
add entry, and yeah this seems like it's
working. View all, and here we have "Hey There".
Close, so we were able to create
a class and put all the functions inside
the class, so we have an organized
program now, and so that's
object-oriented programming,
but object-oriented programming is not
simply about putting some functions
inside a class. Object oriented
programming is about good design, so this
script it's not probably the best
design that we can come up with. Why is that?
Because we're not making use of the
real advantages that we have by using
classes, so what I mean is that here we
are creating these methods and in each
method we're executing some closed
functions, and also creating a connection
in each of the methods. So we can reduce
this code further more buried by
removing the repeated actions, so in a
class of what you need to think about is
a way of constructing something at first,
so in the init function, and then you
refer to that something
in the other functions, in the
other methods, so we're talking about
methods here. So even though our script
is working fine
in the next lecture we will go ahead and
improve the design of it.
So I'll see you there.