Good, we were able to transform our
script which was built using functions,
and we created a class and put those
functions inside that class, so they are now
called methods. And while this is a use
of a class, it's still not the best use
of object-oriented programming paradigm
because we have a database here,
a database object that is being created
but we are not treating it as a solid
object, so we are opening it and closing
it in every method, so what I'm thinking
is we create a connection when we call
the class, so when this function is
executed we create a connection there,
and we keep the connection opened, so I
don't include this close method there,
but I'll leave the commit method in
case there is no table, and a table will
be created and the changes will be
committed to the open connection.
Now because we have a connection open there
we don't need to establish a new one in
each method and we don't even need to
create a cursor object because the
cursor object is being created in here.
So we get rid of those two lines in
every single method. So in view we have a
cursor object when we go here and then
we execute this statement to that cursor
object, so that is good. Then we go down
here, this to as well,
and for the delete method.
And update as well. Great.
Now let's see how this goes.
Let me make this closer, so we call the
frontend script where we are creating an
instance of our object, so far so good.
View all and it says that name cur
is not defined in line 17.
So we executed the view method, and what
the view method does is it tries to find
a variable, a declared variable inside
the function, so the cur variable.
It doesn't find so then it looks if there
is a variable outside the function and
it doesn't find it. Actually there is a
variable that has been declared in this
init function, but this is a local
variable, so this has value only inside
this function, so you cannot access this
outside of the init function. But if we
refer to the self argument which is the
database object, and see what we get.
Let me close this. Save, and that works and
view all, and now we get another type of error.
And it says attribute error, so let me close
this, so look carefully here and it says
database object has no attribute cur.
And that's in line 17, so this one here.
And the database object, this one is this
on here, so self has very placed by
database which is the object created by
this class and this is an attribute of
this object and to fix that we need to
create an attribute there.
So we say self dot cursor, dot cur
equals to connection dot cursor.
the cursor method of the connection
object of the sqlite3, a library.
Now if we try again the code, it says name
cur is not defined in line 8. So now that
we created an attribute, this is
trying to find the variable cur, so the
local variable cur which is not in
this function because now this is an
attribute of the class so that means we
need to refer to self here as well, so to
the object and then cur execute and so on.
So if we try this now view all, we get
another line. Cur is not defined in line 18.
So here, that means you need to do the
same and we don't have any curve
variable anymore. We have the cur attribute.
So now if I run this again I'll get
probably an error about the connection
this time. The conn variable. View all.
Conn is not defined in line 19, so again
this view function is trying to find the
variable conn, connection, so self
commit there and here as well, so you
declare the attribute there, and then you commit
the changes down here, and self connection,
close, so that looks good now. Rows is equal
to this, so rows is just a local variable.
That is created here and then we
returned the fetched rows from
this expression, so this method returns
this when it's being called in this
script, just here, good.
And let me try what we have at this point.
Line seven, name conn is not defined.
Yeah, we need to do the same
for these two, and everything looks good
now, so let's try again. Yeah, view all and
now we get the data there, but when I
press it for the second time we get yet
another error, and so it says cannot
operate on a closed database, so why is that?
Well I pressed the view button once and
this method was executed, so the cursor
object was able to fetch these data, and
then we closed the connection, I returned
the rows, so we are able to get those
three rows there, but then when I pressed
the view button for a second time,
the view method faces a close connection.
So that's why you get this cannot operate
on a closed database error.
So, see what we get.
So view all. It's working well, yep.
That means we can go ahead and modify the
other methods, so self cursor and self
connection, and remove this close.
Let's think about closing the connection
later on, so don't focus on that now.
Just try to make these methods work.
Self here, self there, and there, again for
the delete method, and yeah remove
the connection, close.
And everything should work fine at this
point so let's see. View all. This is
working, let's search for something. "The Sea"
and search entry. We got one cursor there.
So cur is not defined in search.
Oh yeah, sorry! Again. View all.
View all. "The Sea" search entry and yet
another name error.
The name rows is not defined.
So by mistake I converted this
local variable to attributes, so rows
here, rows there. Okay one more time.
View all. View all. Now it seems to be working.
So let's add some data. Add entry there.
And cannot operate on closed database.
Why?
Because all in the search method we have
a closed database, so we closed the
database there, and I overlooked that,
so we don't have any more closed methods
there, no. So let's try one more time then.
Sorry about that!
Add entry and now it seems to be working
fine, great, so everything looks good
except of we don't have the close
method anymore because we can't keep
that method in the methods of our class.
Because you saw that when we have that
method there and we end up
with this error.
Or you can leave the code without
a close method, but you'd end up with some
problems later because if you have some
methods that have not been committed,
then one when another program connects
to your database, then these data
will be committed with the next
operation, so it messes something up
sometimes, so as a rule you should close
the connection, and to do that there is
another special method that you can add
to your class like this one here, but
this other one is for destructing your
object. That is called del, so for delete.
And this also gets the object instance
as a parameter, so this method is applied,
it's executed when you call an instance
of the class like we are doing in the
frontend script, just here, while this
one here it is executed when this
instance is deleted from the script
which happens to be when the script is
exited, so before the script exits this
method will be executed. And what we want
to do here is self dot connection dot close.
So that should do the trick. Now if
we try out this, we should get the same
results, so I added this by mistake but
anyway, so "The Sea". You can search for that.
And you get the rows with that particular
value, so this is my solution
and there's no standard way to write
a script so there may be other
alternatives to solve this problem,
so to build this application so you may
also choose to add a method there or
here in the graphical user interface so
you could do something like you add
a button like commit button,
and then here you add another
method called commit, and then you remove
probably all these commit methods from these
methods, from the methods of your SQLite
operations, and then you put that method,
so one method commit inside that commit
method of your class. So when the user
presses commit, then you commit the changes
to the database, so that would be
another solution, but this is what we
came up with in this particular case, so
I hope you understand a few things now.
This is rarely used, so normally you
only have to use init and then the
other methods, but this is appropriate
when you want to apply something just
before exiting the program, so that's
great and in the next lecture I will
write another class, so we will think
about how to model a problem which is
about creating some sort of bank account
object where we store a balance of money,
Then we withdraw and deposited money
to this balance. Now as an exercise
you can convert this script, so the tkinter
part of the program, the frontend
into an object-oriented form so you put
these inside a class and try to come up
with a good solution. I'll also provide
you a solution to this, but before that I
would like you to try out yourself, so you
practice object-oriented programming
a little bit. Yeah, that's good. With that
I'll see you in the next lecture.