Hello again, and in this lecture I would
like to make sure you know the
terminology of object-oriented
programming in Python, so now we have the
class which is this blueprint here or
you can call it a prototype that defines
the characteristics of an object that is
about to be created, so that's the class.
And then we have the object instance,
or simply the object, so this here is
an object, so a checking account
object that stores data in this specific
file path and it has this attribute so
it has this fee. Then we have instance
variables, and these are variables that
are defined inside the methods of the
class like file path here, and these are
accessible by the instance, so by the object
instance that is created by that class.
Then we also have something called class
variable, so instance variables, and class
variables. Now we didn't create a class
variable in any of the previous lectures
so I'll go ahead and create one now.
Let's create one for our checking
account, so that would be something like
let's say type equals to checking, so
a class variable is declared outside of
the methods of that class, and class
variables are shared by all the
instances of a class, so instance variables
are shared by only the object instance.
For instance let me explain that. Here
this is one of our object instances,
so we only have one object instance here,
but we could have more, so I'll copy this
and create another object instance here.
And I'll call this, let's say this is
Jack's checking account, so I'll replace
that, and that, and that. This is
John's checking account, and they also
have their personal storage there, so let's
say Jack dot txt and John dot txt.
So Jack has 100 dollars, and John has
200 dollars. Good, so we need to
change that, Jack's, Jack,
and John, and if we execute this
script now, we will get two values
printed out, so minus 1 for this statement
here because Jack had, so he had $100
there, but when he transferred 100 and
then minus the fee of $1 and then he
ended up with minus 1 dollar there.
He owns the bank some money, and then
John had 200 so he has 99 now.
So what I'm trying to say is that these
variables belong only to their object,
but if you try now Jack's checking dot
type, so you want to print that, print
John's checking dot type. You'll see
that this a class variable is shared by
all the instances of that class.
So that's the difference between class
and instance variables. Class variables
are rarely used,
so you'll really have to pass them in here.
Another concept now, doc strings
and a doc stirring is usually passed
as soon as you ride the class keyword,
so just down the class keyword and that
provides the explanation of your class.
Let's say this class generates checking
account object, and then you close that
with three quotes, so what that does is
you know if we print that out, so we grab
one of our object instances, let's say
John's checking dot double underscore doc
and double under score again, so print that.
So as you see a doc string is used to
provide some information about that
class, so it's good to define this string
when you're writing classes so that
others if they use your class and they
can apply this operation here and they can
see what your class is about. This is
particularly useful when you're
importing classes from modules, so when
you don't actually see the code of your
class, and you can do this and you can,
you have access to the doc string of the
class, and then we have the concept
of data members which actually is referred
to class variables or instance variables.
So this is a data member, and this also is
a data member as well. Then we have the
constructor which was this init function.
And as you know the init function, so the
constructor constructs your class. Then
you have class methods that you apply to
your object instance, so transfer is a
class method, so this is also a method
but it's a special method, so it's
a constructor, and instantiation if you
hear about instantiation that is the
process of creating object
instances, so instances of a class like
this is instantiation of the class,
and this one here as well, and you know
inheritance now. Inheritance is when you
create a subclass out of a base class.
And this subclass shares the methods of
the base class plus it has its own
methods that are specific to that
subclass. Sometimes you also hear about
attributes and attributes are these one
here, so when you access these instance
variables, or even, so class variables,
or even instance variables, you can say
you're accessing attributes of your
class instance, so of your object. And yeah,
that's about the vocabulary of object-oriented
programming in Python.
I really believe I have given you
a solid understanding of object-oriented
programming, and creating classes and
objects and so on. If you still find
something confusing
you can either rewatch your videos
because I know object-oriented
programming is a bit tricky, but you can
even ask questions, and I'll make my best
to explain things that are not yet
clear to you, and I hope you find this
useful, and I'll talk you in the next
lectures, so we're done with this
section, and yeah, see you later.